<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The modest critick, or, Remarks upon the most eminent historians, antient and modern with useful cautions and instructions as well for writing as reading history : wherein the sense of the greatest men on this subject is faithfully abridged / by one of the Society of the Port-Royal.</title>
            <author>One of the Society of the Port-Royal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22028</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12485943</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12485943</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62282</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58060)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62282)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 290:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The modest critick, or, Remarks upon the most eminent historians, antient and modern with useful cautions and instructions as well for writing as reading history : wherein the sense of the greatest men on this subject is faithfully abridged / by one of the Society of the Port-Royal.</title>
                  <author>One of the Society of the Port-Royal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[23], 151 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Barnes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, October the 9th, 1688. Rob. Midgely"--P. [1].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:62282:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Licenſed,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>October</hi> the 9<hi>th.</hi>
1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Rob. Midgley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62282:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE Modeſt Critick: OR REMARKS Upon the moſt Eminent HISTORIANS, Antient and Modern. With Uſeful Cautions and Inſtructions, as well for Writing, as Reading HISTORY: Wherein the Senſe of the Greateſt Men on this Subject is faithfully Abridged.</p>
            <p>By one of the Society of the <hi>Port-Royal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Barnes,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Bear</hi> and <hi>Ragged Staff,</hi> in <hi>Green-Street,</hi> near
<hi>Leiceſter-Square.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:62282:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62282:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IT is as unuſual for a Book to be Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd without a
<hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face,</hi> as for a man to go abroad without a Cravat: Something therefore muſt be ſaid, for Faſhion ſake: But, becauſe I am no way addicted to Garb and <pb facs="tcp:62282:3"/> Dreſs, what I ſay ſhall be plain and ſhort.</p>
            <p>I have liv'd long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in the World, to know, that a man who ventures to make any Work of his own Publick, puts himſelf into Extream Danger of being attack'd on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſide, and by all ſort of People, as well Learned as Ignorant; and theſe are the worſt of the two; for a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable man may be <pb facs="tcp:62282:3"/> ſatisfied with Reaſon, when a Fool will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be convinc'd of his Error. This has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways made me unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to expoſe any thing of my own: But, having receiv'd, in the peruſing of this little Book, both Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Profit, I thought it would be but matter of Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in me, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:62282:4"/> The Preſs having of late been proſtituted to the Dull and Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, it will be no great Credit for me to run in the Herd, much leſs to bring up the Rear of them that are in Print.</p>
            <p>It is not therefore from Vanity, or the fond imagination of rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a Character, that I ſend this little Treatiſe abroad; but meerly, that others, who have <pb facs="tcp:62282:4"/> the ſame Notions with my ſelf, may receive from it the ſame ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that I have done.</p>
            <p>It is not now, as heretofore, when he that could write, or read his Name, was thought therefore fit to be a <hi>Pariſh-Clerk: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunatus,</hi> and <hi>Valentine</hi> and <hi>Orſon,</hi> &amp;c. are no longer the Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Men. Nay, ſo ripe and pretending is the preſent Age, that <pb facs="tcp:62282:5"/> Women paſs their time in the beſt and ſolideſt Hiſtories.</p>
            <p>But tho' many read, yet all do not read with Judgment and Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therefore they may learn in reading this Book, inſtructions how to read and write too.</p>
            <p>Now to do my ſelf ſome Right, I muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly confeſs, there are ſome Paſſages, about which I am not fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, as about the <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiates</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:62282:5"/> and
<hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> tho' the Author has <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lybius</hi> on his ſide.</p>
            <p>He has not done ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to the World, in not mentioning ſome late Hiſtorians; I mean, amongſt the reſt, <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus</hi> and
<hi>Sleidan,</hi> who deſerve not to be paſs'd over in ſilence.</p>
            <p>It is not to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, that one of the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> ſhould ſo ſharply cenſure the incomparable <hi>Fra Pao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:62282:6"/> whoſe <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> carried him beyond their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and whoſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty was above their Calumny: But the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the <hi>Council of Trent</hi> is ſufficient to maintain that Author's Credit againſt all their Suggeſtions.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France</hi>'s buſying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf about the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Caeſar's Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries,</hi> I muſt beg the
<pb facs="tcp:62282:6"/> Author's Pardon, if I cannot believe him, That <hi>Monarch</hi> having buſineſs enough of his own, without medling with <hi>Books.</hi> And, I am confident, had He never done more than <hi>Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of that Book, He had never had the Name of <hi>Louis Le Grand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, for theſe, and other ſuch Faults, I will leave every Reader to take the ſame Liberty towards him that he has <pb facs="tcp:62282:7"/> taken with others. To ſay the Truth, He that ſets up for a <hi>Critick,</hi> offers a Challenge to the whole World: Therefore, not to be remark'd upon, is the laſt Affront that can be put upon him. But I forget the Complaint I made of other People's ſcribling, while I thus far continue my own.
<hi>Reader,</hi> accept this with the ſame Mind that I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it; And ſo
<hi>Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62282:7"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>I Have neither ſo good an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of this <hi>Work,</hi> nor of my ſelf, as to prefix my <hi>Name</hi> to it; it being but a rough Draught of the <hi>Manner</hi> of writing <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> and that made upon a curſory reading of <hi>Hiſtory.</hi> A Natural Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence I have of my ſelf, makes me fear, leſt <hi>Impatience</hi> or <hi>Precipitation</hi> has ſnatch'd <pb facs="tcp:62282:8"/> out of my hands what could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver remain too long with me, to render it ſelf any way ſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But that I may not diſguſt the <hi>Publick</hi> too much, by repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the <hi>Preſent</hi> I here make it, <hi>too mean</hi> and <hi>cheap:</hi> I ſhall ingenuouſly confeſs, That this Work is a kind of <hi>Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of what has been
<hi>written</hi> on that <hi>Subject,</hi> by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Men of the firſt, and of the late Ages; That it is an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract</hi> of what is moſt reaſonable in <hi>Dionyſius Halycarnaſſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Pompey,</hi> who ask'd his Opinion of the <hi>Greek Hiſtorians,</hi> and his <hi>Cenſure</hi> upon their <hi>different Characters:</hi> That it is a <pb facs="tcp:62282:8"/> 
               <hi>Copy</hi> of what
<hi>Lucian</hi> has thought moſt judicious in that Admirable Treatiſe he made <hi>of the Manner of Writing HISTORY.</hi> In fine, That thoſe
<hi>Opinions</hi> I give in this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> are not ſo much my own, as thoſe of <hi>Franceſco Patrici,</hi> in his <hi>Dialogues</hi> of
<hi>Gyrolamo Marucci, Agoſtino Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardi,</hi> of <hi>Paolo Beni, Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is Cabrera,</hi> and others, <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> and <hi>Italian Moderns,</hi> which have handled this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But, as perhaps, I have ſpoil'd their Thoughts by add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my own, I declare, That I do not make it a Point of <pb facs="tcp:62282:9"/> Honour to my ſelf, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my Readers of it.
<note n="a" place="margin">Cum judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium meum oſtendere, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am legentibus relinquam. <hi>Fab.</hi> l. 9. c. 4.</note> I do not impoſe Laws upon them, having neither Juriſdiction nor Authority to do ſo; they are, at the moſt, but <hi>Advices,</hi> which every one may follow at his <hi>own Diſcretion:</hi> But, being far from pretending to <hi>inſtruct</hi> any body, by a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle which ſhall ſeem vain to <hi>Modeſt Perſons,</hi> I would willingly have all the World believe, that I am <hi>proud</hi> of receiving <hi>any Inſtruction</hi> from others. For, if I have <hi>not Wit</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, to be as <hi>Exact</hi> as ſo
<hi>Important a Deſign</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; I have <hi>Judgement</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:62282:9"/> enough to be fearful of my ſelf. But, that I may not take a <hi>Falſe Modeſty</hi> upon me, by ſuppreſſing my <hi>Name,</hi> I confeſs, that, in a manner, I conceal my ſelf out of Pride: For I am too proud to ſhew my ſelf, being ſenſible, that in an Age ſo <hi>Learned,</hi> and ſo full of <hi>Criticks,</hi> as ours is, a Man humbles himſelf, whenever he takes up the <hi>Name</hi> of an <hi>Author.</hi> In effect, their
<hi>Rigour</hi> is ſo great, that no <hi>Merit,</hi> how well ſoever eſtabliſhed, can eſcape them; And it looks like a kind of
<hi>Preſumption</hi> in a Man, to commit himſelf o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly to the
<hi>Judgement</hi> of <pb facs="tcp:62282:10"/> the <hi>Publick,</hi> which daily becomes more rigorous; and in an Age where <hi>Cenſure</hi> ſpares no body. It is alſo true, That there is ſo great a <hi>Wiſdom</hi> in not endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſeem <hi>capable;</hi> and that there is ſo much <hi>good Senſe</hi> ſhew'd in being <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt,</hi> that I could willingly have choſen to add, in thoſe places where I give my <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> the <hi>May be</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,</hi> and the <hi>It ſeems</hi> of <hi>Tully,</hi> to be
<hi>leſs Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and to ſpeak my Mind with <hi>more Modeſty,</hi> could that have ſuited with the <hi>Simplicity</hi> I uſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain my ſelf. For, if a <pb facs="tcp:62282:10"/> Man has any <hi>Meaſure of Senſe,</hi> he will hardly give his <hi>Opinion,</hi> in an Age ſo over-run with <hi>Poſitiveneſs</hi> in all things, as ours is; and then, Wo be to him that offers to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide.</p>
            <p>Therefore this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> upon <hi>Hiſtory</hi> is no ways like that of <hi>Lucian</hi>'s, who prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes good <hi>Writers</hi> only to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from thoſe that <hi>write ill;</hi> hiding, under the
<hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation</hi> which he gives to <hi>Good Authors,</hi> a cunning
<hi>Satyr,</hi> the more to involve the <hi>bad ones:</hi> That is not my
<hi>Deſign,</hi> having no Grudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Man. I pretend on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to open ſenſible Author's <pb facs="tcp:62282:11"/> Eyes, and ſhew them, that they ought to tremble when they go about writing <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which is ſo hard a thing to do well; and that the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Dionyſius Haly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnaſſaeus</hi> alone upon <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydides,</hi> ought to caſt a Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in all <hi>Hiſtorian's</hi> Minds that are wiſe. In fine, to ſpeak one Word about this <hi>Work,</hi> after I have ſpoken of the
<hi>Workman,</hi> I declare, that <hi>good ſenſe</hi> alone reigns more in thoſe <hi>Inſtructions,</hi> than the <hi>Fineſſes</hi> of
<hi>Policy;</hi> which is the thing curious men look moſt for in
<hi>Hiſtory, Policy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Vaineſt</hi> of all
<hi>Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> and that, <hi>good Senſe,</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:62282:11"/> is the
<hi>moſt univerſal</hi> and <hi>ſolid ground</hi> thereof. The Truth is, That I do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſay all upon that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which no man can do: I ſhall, perhaps, ſay more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other time, if this be kindly receiv'd.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:62282:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62282:12"/>
            <head>THE Modeſt Critick: OR, REMARKS Upon the moſt Eminent HISTORIANS.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Deſign of the Author.</note> THE Palate of this Age, it ſeems, grows very exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite; for in all things, for the moſt part, we attain a good meaſure of Senſe: We e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem that which is Real and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, and we can hardly now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure any thing that is falſe or fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous. This is the Sentiment of all reaſonable People, who make the ſoundeſt part of them that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to judge, thô it be perhaps the leſſer in number.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62282:13"/> But nothing ſhews that ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Judgment better than the Diſguſt People have now for <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances,</hi> and any other thing that looks like them; ſo that this love of Truth and Reaſon, being a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to love <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> let us make uſe of ſo favourable a Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, to ſerve the Publick accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Genius; let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow our pains in thoſe things that can make us perfect in that Art; and comprehending the excellence thereof, let us make our ſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with thoſe things that are needful to attain it: For, what Spirit is not requiſite for it? and what can we imagine finer than
<note n="b" place="margin">Pulchrum imprimis vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, non pati occidere, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aeternitas debeatur. <hi>Pl. l.</hi> 5.
<hi>Epiſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> which can do juſtice to
<hi>Virtue,</hi> by perpetuating the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Noble Actions? This is, in my mind, what can contribute to the Perfection, of which this kind of writing is capable, which will carry it above all other (if that love for Senſe which eſtabliſhes it ſelf can but continue) in deſpite of the variety of taſts, which fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and vanity endeavour from time <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62282:13"/> to time to introduce thrô falſe Ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a's of fine wit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>I.How to write Hiſtory.</head>
               <p>There is nothing harder than to ſay very preciſely which is the beſt way of writing Hiſtory. Every one ought to follow that which he finds moſt in Uſe in the Age where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he writes, and that which is moſt conformable to thoſe Peoples taſte to whom he writes. But, is this enough to pleaſe Poſterity? It is a Judge ſtrict, ſevere, incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, who gives its approbation to true Merit only: let us ſee then what we ſhall do to obtain its ſuffrage. When a man writes Nobly, Senſibly, Purely, Natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; he pleaſes always in what Language ſoever he writes. Thoſe are the univerſal Principles, which alone can fit every People's palate<hi>:</hi> for there are no other general Rules in the World, than thoſe of Reaſon and good Senſe. That is the reaſon why <hi>Thucidides, Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon,</hi> 
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62282:14"/> 
                  <hi>Saluſt, Caeſar, Livy, Buchanan, Mariana,</hi> and others like them, have always pleas'd, though they wrote in Ages, and to Nations of a different genius<hi>:</hi> a man is ſure to pleaſe, if he writes as they have writ. For, what Grandeur, what Judgment, what Clearneſs, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, what Integrity ſhines in thoſe great men's Works!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>II. What to write nobly is.</head>
               <p>You muſt then reſolve to write nobly, if you deſign to write <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.</hi> For,
<note n="c" place="margin">Genus hoc ſcribendi inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum atque elatum eſle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere quis ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norat? <hi>Cic.</hi> ad <hi>Famil. Epiſt.</hi>
7. <hi>l.</hi> 6.</note> from the moment you ſpeak to all the world, and to all Ages, you are endued with a Character which gives you au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to raiſe your voice, becauſe then you ſpeak to <hi>Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and to the
<hi>Grandees</hi> of all <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries</hi> and of all <hi>Ages;</hi> and you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, in ſome manner, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Inſtructer of all mankind<hi>:</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Addidit Hiſtoriae ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorem ſonum vocis Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, caeteri non exornatores rerum, ſed tantummodo narratores ſuerunt. <hi>Cic. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de Orat.</hi>
                  </note> Nothing, then, is more eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> than to adorn your <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62282:14"/> diſcourſe with a lofty ſtrain, to ſpeak as you ought. As an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian quits the low and common Language, that ſo by the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Expreſſion, he may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the merit of thoſe things he has to ſay<hi>:</hi> let him uſe himſelf to think nobly, in every thing that paſſes through his mind: let him ſtudy to give good weight to his thoughts, and ſtrength to his diſcourſe, by ſeeking with care all that can elevate and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble it, to give a mark of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to all that he ſays. The Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of that kind of writing, are, amongſt the <hi>Greeks Thucydides,</hi> and <hi>Livy</hi> amongſt the <hi>Latins.</hi> They are almoſt the only ones that have been able to keep up with an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual force and vigour, that great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Style, without ſinking in <hi>Mediocrity</hi> and <hi>Lowneſs:</hi> and in that they have had but few Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators.
<hi>Herodotus</hi> has, by imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Homer</hi> too much, tryed to raiſe his Style in places that requir'd elevation, as <hi>Longinus</hi> has taken notice. <hi>Tacitus,</hi> who for the moſt <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62282:15"/> part is only great, becauſe he is ſhort, is not a very good model to propoſe, for the greatneſs of his Style is not natural at all. In ſhort, you muſt take great care to diſtinguiſh a falſe greatneſs from the true one. For, it is not in high terms, nor in lofty expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; it is not in the puffing of words, nor haughtineſs of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, that that nobleneſs of Style which <hi>Hiſtory</hi> requires, ought to conſiſt; in which
<hi>Ammianus Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellinus, Lampridius,</hi> and moſt part of the
<hi>Hiſtorians</hi> of the low <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> have been deceived<hi>:</hi> It is in a high, but modeſt Expreſſion; in a Diſcourſe capable of ſuſtaining the greateſt matters and raiſing the leaſt; It is, in fine, in that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of greatneſs, which <hi>Quintillian</hi> attributes to true <hi>Eloquence.</hi> It is not enough for you to have Wit,
<note n="e" place="margin">Magna, non nimia, ſublimis non abrupta, ſortis non temeraria, ſevera non tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis, gravis non tarda, lata non luxurioſa, ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na non tumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da. <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi>
10.</note> you muſt have a genius to write ſo, and to elevate what you ſay, by the choice of <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> and by the greatneſs of your <hi>thoughts.</hi> That gift is ſo rare, that if you ſeparate from the number of <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians,</hi> 
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62282:15"/> thoſe that have not writ ſo, there will be but few true ones that will remain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>III. To write ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly.</head>
               <p>To write ſenſibly, is to hit di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly the thing you aim at, in what kind ſoever you write, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out going from your Subject, or loſing time by the way: It is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs things with a kind of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Modeſty,</hi> not abandoning your ſelf to the heat of your
<hi>Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> nor to the quickneſs of your <hi>Apprehenſion;</hi> that is, when you can ſuppreſs that which is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous in the Expreſſion, as thoſe <hi>Adverbs</hi> and <hi>Epithets</hi> which dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh things, as they expreſs them; to let no <hi>idle, inſipid,</hi> and uſeleſs thing remain in it<hi>:</hi> to cut off hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly, what is not fit to be ſaid, how fine ſoever it appears; to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ever leſs to fineneſs, than to Solidity; not to ſhew Paſſion or Heat, where only cold Blood and Seriouſneſs are requir'd; to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62282:16"/> all your thoughts,
<note n="f" place="margin">Delectus Verborum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendus, &amp; pondera ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulorum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminanda. <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure all your words, with that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs of ſenſe, and that exquiſite Judgment, which nothing eſcapes, but what is exact and judicious. It is, in fine, to have Strength e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to reſiſt the temptation Men have naturally to ſhew their Wit;
<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> de conſer. Hiſt.</note> as that Impertinent <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian,</hi> who in the
<hi>Parthian</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw by the <hi>Emperour Severus,</hi> makes
<hi>Oſroes</hi> fly in a Den ſhaded with <hi>Lawrels</hi> and
<hi>Myrtle,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he makes himſelf ridiculous, thinking to be more agreeable, which is the moſt ſlippery ſtep an Author can fall upon. And that Spirit endued with Senſe, that wiſe Character which Hiſtory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, is a kind of attendance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ones ſelf, which allows it ſelf no manner of Exaggeration, and which takes endleſs Precautions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe bold Imaginations; which thoſe, whoſe Spirits are too quick or too fertile, are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to; that they may ſay few things in few words, as
<hi>Saluſt</hi> does, who holds <hi>Councils,</hi> gives <hi>Battels,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62282:16"/> takes <hi>Towns,</hi> conquers <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> with a compendiouſneſs of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> and an overflowing
<hi>Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> which is underſtood at half Sentences.
<hi>Tacitus</hi> has all the Senſe neceſſary to be ſhort; but he has not enough on't to be underſtood. The <hi>Readers</hi> grow ſometimes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient in that Author's Precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which loſes much of his agreeableneſs, and trying to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact in too few words, that which ſhould have been more extended, falls into Obſcurity. The deſire he has of being too ſhort, angers me, becauſe of the ſmall Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he gives me in things, which he does not unfold enough. <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> and <hi>Appian</hi> ſometimes ſay too much; there is a ſort of judicious ſilence, which makes one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend often the greatneſs of the things one ſpeaks of, better than any words, when they are too weak. It is a Maſter-piece for one to ſuppreſs thoſe things he cannot well ſay; and the great Diſcretion in an <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> is to make a diſtinction of what muſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62282:17"/> be extended, or made ſhort, that ſo he may give to every thing the juſt meaſure it ought to have, to make it acceptable. For
<hi>Livy,</hi> thô very large, is not tedious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is a Man of Judgment, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in his very Prolixity. But <hi>Thucydides,</hi> by ſticking too cloſe to Senſe, ſometimes falls in a kind of hardneſs and dryneſs, which one would hardly forgive him, was it not for the pureneſs and noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Style. So difficult it is to write very ſenſibly, without lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſomewhat of the agreeableneſs which one might employ, if he had a leſſer Wit. But let an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor imprint well in his Mind, that the greateſt Ornament of his Work, is always good Senſe; all the reſt wearies one, but Senſe never tires. 'Twas the good Senſe of <hi>Philip de Comines,</hi> made him juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerve the eſteem and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of our Age, in deſpight of the bad and ill-digeſted Language he wrote in. But of all Modern <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> none has written more ſenſibly than
<hi>Mariana</hi> in his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <pb n="11" facs="tcp:62282:17"/> of <hi>Spain.</hi> It is the Maſter-piece of the laſt Ages for that quality a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. In all that Work a Genius appears, which keeps him always from neglecting himſelf in choice Points, and from abandoning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in thoſe that are not ſo. And this judicious equality, which that Author always obſerves, thô the matters he treats of be never ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal, is little known to our late
<hi>Hiſtorians.</hi> But the Art of thinking ſenſibly of things, is not ſufficient, unleſs he has alſo that of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them purely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>IV. To write purely.</head>
               <p>An <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> who thinks to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his Book to future Ages, muſt think of
<note n="h" place="margin">Hiſtorico ſermoni de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus conciliet, perſpicuitas, proprietaſque verborum. <hi>Beni lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Hiſtor.</hi>
                  </note> writing pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Without that advantage, an
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> will be but ſhort liv'd. For want of
<note n="i" place="margin">Quid tam neceſſarium quam recta lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutio? <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 1.</note> purity of Style, ſo many <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin Hiſtorians,</hi> of whom <hi>Photius,</hi> and the other Library-keepers, have made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, have periſh'd in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſhipwrack of ſo many Books; <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62282:18"/> and that, of a number almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, of whom
<note n="k" place="margin">Cura ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gna ſentiendi &amp; loquendi, ſed diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio curae prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipua. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note>
                  <hi>Voſſius</hi> ſpeaks, none remain, but thoſe that have writ reaſonably enough to deſerve to be read. You muſt not then pretend to write <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> unleſs you very well know the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage you intend to write in, and, except you write purely. For, as ſoon as your deſign is to inſtruct, you ought to think how to expreſs your ſelf neatly, that you may be underſtood; for when a man ſpeaks well, every one is willing to hear him: beſides, one that ſpeaks ill, never ſpeaks any thing right;
<note n="l" place="margin">Nihil eſt in Hiſtoria, pura &amp; illuſtri brevitate dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius. <hi>Cic. in Brut.</hi>
                  </note> and that clearneſs, which is the greateſt charm in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> can only be found in a pure Style. That purity conſiſts chiefly in the propriety of words; in the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ordering of the phraſes, and in the wiſe and moderate uſe of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures. The ſtyle ought not to have any thing
<note n="m" place="margin">In Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia nihil abſurdum, aut alienum, aut ſubinſulſum; in verbis nihil inquinatum, abjectum, non aptum, durum, longe petitum, <hi>Cic. de op. gen. orat.</hi>
                  </note> improper, ſtrange, bold, hard, creeping nor obſcure. <hi>Herodotus</hi> has that purity <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62282:18"/> of ſtyle, and has excelled in it, above all other
<hi>Grecians,</hi> as <hi>Caeſar</hi> above all the <hi>Latins.</hi> The Wits of the following Ages grew ruſty, and retain'd little of the purity of the
<hi>Ancients.</hi> But <hi>Quintus Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> thinking to appear more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd, has loſt ſomewhat of that great and majeſtick grace, which becomes <hi>Saluſt</hi> and <hi>Livy</hi> ſo well. It is true that he flouriſhes ſome places too much; as for example, the Deſcription of the River <hi>Marſyas,</hi> in the beginning of the third Book; The Adventure of
<hi>Abdolonymus,</hi> who, from a Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, became King, in the fourth Book: Of the ſiege of <hi>Tyre,</hi> and of a great many others, where it appears an affectation of <hi>Eloquence</hi> little becomming the Gravity of
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> which can bear nothing that is affected. Indeed, that puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Elocution ſo neceſſary to <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> ought to be ſupported by a great deal of Senſe. For,
<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <p>Non debet quiſquam ubi maxima re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum momenta verſantur, ſollicitus eſſe de verbis, <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</p>
                     <p>Ut monilibus &amp; margaritis quae ſunt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namenta Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarum, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formantur Viri, nec ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalis quo ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil auguſtius, foeminas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</p>
                     <p>Ornatus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis non tam ſua, quam rei cui adhibetur conditione conſtat. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> nothing is more fulſome than
<hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence,</hi> when empty of things, and which ſays nothing. It hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62282:19"/> that, ſometimes, purity of Diſcourſe too much ſtudied in great Subjects, diminiſhes its great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; as it appears in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Indies</hi> by <hi>Maffaeus,</hi> and in the wars of <hi>Flanders</hi> by <hi>Cardinal Bentivoglio.</hi> The one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have ſtudied too much how to pleaſe by the Politeneſs of the diſcourſe, not remembring, that Beautys that are ſprucely attir'd ſmite leaſt, and that the fineſt ornaments diſguiſe a thing, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they are exceſſive and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>V. To write with Simplicity.</head>
               <p>You are alſo obliged to write with ſimplicity, to avoid that Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous and that affected Air, which are both ſo contrary to that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter which is requir'd in <hi>Hiſtory:</hi> becauſe, whatſoever is great, ceaſes to be ſo as ſoon as it is ſtrip'd of that ſimplicity; and that which is pure and great too, receives an acceſſion of greatneſs, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes lofty.
<note n="o" place="margin">Si oratio perderet gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ſimplicis &amp; inaffectati coloris, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret &amp; fidem. <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 9.
<hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> Nothing alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs, <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62282:19"/> and gets the publick ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, more than that ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Style, ſo beloved of the Ancients, and ſo little known by the Moderns. All that which is exaggerated, ſeems falſe; and Nature, which you ought to have for your object, delights not in impertinent flouriſhes. But that you may exactly underſtand that ſimplicity which is ſo neceſſary to a great Style; you muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that there are three ſorts of it; A ſimplicity in words, as that of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> a ſimplicity in the Thoughts, as that of
<hi>Saluſt,</hi> a ſimplicity in the Deſign, as that of
<hi>Thucydides,</hi> ſo much valued by
<note n="p" place="margin">In judicio de <hi>Thucydide.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Dionyſius Halicarnaſſaeus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Moderns,</hi> which have come the neareſt to that Character, are, amongſt the <hi>French, Phillip de Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines; Guichardin</hi> amongſt the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, Buchanan</hi> in <hi>Scotland, Mariana</hi> amongſt the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the reſt, ſeek only to maintain themſelves by the Purity, Politeneſs, and other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of Diſcourſe, when they <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62282:20"/> have not a Spirit great enough to attain that ſimplicity; and they diſguiſe the Truth, when they want ſtrength to ſhew it naked. Happy is the Man that can attain it, when he makes writing his Buſineſs; thoſe that are ignorant may underſtand it, at the ſame time that the intelligent are charm'd with it. But nothing is harder to get, than that plain and natural way, which makes the ſimplicity of the Style. A Genius extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary is requir'd to expreſs things clearly, without dropping into a low and cold ſtyle. For at the ſame time that you endeavour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſimplicity, you ought to dread nothing more than flatneſs: What is then, that admirable ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is the higheſt perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a great work, and wherein do's it conſiſt?
<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Homerus</hi> brevem qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem cum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi jucundita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, propriam, carentem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluis elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiam
<hi>Menelao</hi> dedit, quae ſunt virtutes generls primi. <hi>Fab. l.</hi>
12. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> It is to make uſe only of the moſt common and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt words, but they muſt always be full of a great ſenſe, as that Prince do's, to whom <hi>Homer</hi> gives <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62282:20"/> a brief Eloquence, agreeable, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, without ſuperfluity.
<note n="r" place="margin">Exponere ſimpliciter
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ulla Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione <hi>Cic. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de Invent.</hi>
                  </note> It is to think and ſpeak juſt what you have to ſay and to think, without giving too much quickneſs to your expreſſion, as <hi>Strada</hi> do's; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving too great a brightneſs to your thoughts, as <hi>Grotius</hi> did. It is to have your Sentiments ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and natural, not making ſo many Arguments and Reflections, as <hi>Davila</hi> in his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: for as ſoon as you argue ſo much, it is no more Nature that ſpeak's, 'tis Art and Study<hi>:</hi> and thoſe diſcourſes ſo labour'd, ſmell of the Schools.
<note n="s" place="margin">Non dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ornatius quam ſimplex ratio veritatis ferat. <hi>Cic. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Orat.</hi>
                  </note> It is not to mix more Ornament in your diſcourſe than the modeſty of the truth can bear. It is to expreſs that natural and free air of
<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Xenophontis</hi> illam ſucundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem inaffec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatam, quam nulla affectatio conſequi poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, upſae ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monen Gratiae finxiſſe vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur. <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 10.
<hi>c. i.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Xenophon,</hi> which no imaginable affectation can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. It is, in fine, to poſſeſs that marvellous talent of paring off the ſuperfluous part of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, of which <hi>Phocian</hi> was ſo excellent a maſter; of whom, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as he was, <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> was wont to ſay, when he ſaw him aſcend <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62282:21"/> the Tribunal, as his Antagoniſt,
<note n="u" place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
                  <hi>Here's the ſword which is going to cut off all the ſuperfluity of my words.</hi> That you may well eſtabliſh that Character, which, beſides a great ſtore of Wiſdom and good Senſe, requires much exerciſe and a great deal of Meditation; you muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the uſe of thoſe Authors whoſe imagination is too full, that you may not fall in that torrent of falſe thoughts, boundleſs expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and thoſe confuſions which have but a glance of good ſenſe, into which you will eaſily fall, if you have not an exact Senſe, and an equal Spirit. You muſt propoſe to your ſelf no other rule of that manner of writing, but the <hi>Ancients.</hi> And, among thoſe, you muſt make choice of them which have moſt of this ſimplicity.
<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenes</hi> propounds
<hi>Theocritus</hi> and <hi>Anacreon</hi> for great Patterns of it: and indeed nothing is opener and freer than what they have writ. <hi>Herodotus</hi> ſeems to <hi>Longinus</hi> too bold. <hi>Dionyſius Halicarnaſſaeus</hi> finds, that <hi>Thucydides,</hi> thô a great Maſter <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62282:21"/> of that Simplicity, loads ſome of his Relations with too much of the matter of fact. <hi>Xenophon</hi> and <hi>Polybius</hi> moralize too much, and often hinder the ſtream of <hi>Hiſtory</hi> by their Reflections.
<hi>Diodorus Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus</hi> mixes too much Learning in his Diſcourſes.
<hi>Plutarch</hi> may go for a great original of that ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city we look after: for every thing he ſays reliſhes of it. <hi>Livy</hi> ſeems not to me more agreeable by all his other great qualities than by that. The ſtream of his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> is like that of a great River which floweth majeſtically, as that of <hi>Tacitus</hi> reſembles a deep and ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling River, ſubject to overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: he never keeps a tenour in his thoughts, but often is immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate in his expreſſions for want of this ſimplicity.
<hi>Mariana</hi> is one of the moſt accompliſh't among the modern
<hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> becauſe he regards it moſt. For the ſimplicity of Style cannot be found in great Subjects, without being accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with greatneſs and noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Thoſe are the qualities from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62282:22"/> whence that firſt ground which <hi>Hiſtory</hi> requires ariſe, and which we may, in a manner, call the firſt Elements of that beauty which it muſt have, and which ought to reign more in the mind, and in all the Character of the <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> than in his Style and in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Here are the other qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities which muſt be added to him to make him perfect, which I touch ſuccinctly, without any other order, than that in which they preſent themſelves to my mind. I begin with the
<hi>Matter</hi> and the <hi>Form;</hi> that is to ſay, with that which is moſt eſſential to <hi>Hiſtory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>VI. The Matter in Hiſtory.</head>
               <p>The Matter fit to exerciſe the Art of an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> is a vaſt field, ſince it extends it ſelf to all the Actions of men,
<hi>viz.</hi> Peace, War, Councils, Negotiations, Ambaſſies, Intrigues, and all the ſeveral Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures which may happen in this life.
<note n="y" place="margin">In rebus magnis, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriaque dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Hiſtoriam verſari. <hi>Cic. de Orat. l.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> requires two quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62282:22"/> in the matter of an
<hi>Hiſtory.</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Hiſtoriam afluetam diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currere per negotiorum celſitudines non humilium minutias inda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare cauſarum.
<hi>Ammian. Marcel. l.</hi> 26.</note> That they may be great things, and ſuch as may be fit to be made publick. None has explain'd bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what choice an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ought to make of his Subject, than <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius Halycarnaſſaeus,</hi> in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of his <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and in his Judgment upon <hi>Thucydides,</hi> where he prefers the choice which
<hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus</hi> has made of his Subject to that of <hi>Thucydides,</hi> for the reaſons which he brings. But, as falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood often reſembles Truth, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a great deal of diſcretion and ſagacity, to make an exact diſtinction of it, to unriddle the true motives of important Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, from their colours and their pretexts, and to chooſe your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument wiſely, which may become curious and fine by the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances well lay'd together, and by the order wherein you muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce that which is too wide and far diffus'd, by reſtraining it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the natural extent of thoſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits it ought to have. When it is ſo reduc'd, let the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> render
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62282:23"/> himſelf Maſter of it by a deep Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation upon his Subject, which he ought intirely to underſtand.
<note n="a" place="margin">Equidem non affirmare ſuſtineo de quibus dubito, nec ſubducere quae accepi. <hi>Curt. l.</hi> 9.</note> But let him alſo be ſo exact and religious, as never to abuſe the Credit of the Publick, by giving his own Conjectures for truth, or certain things for doubtful ones. Let him aſcend, as much as in him lies, to the Spring of the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions he ſhall have given him, to make a juſt diſtinction of them. Let him never aſſure things upon common Reports, of which the Authors are always uncertain. Let him deliver them upon very ſure Memoirs, and upon very faithful Relations. Let him not abandon himſelf too raſhly to the
<hi>Hiſtorians</hi> which have been before him, leſt he ſhould loſe his way by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ill Guides. Let him make a great difference between thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations that are intereſted, or ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of Prejudice, and thoſe that are not ſo. Let him always have a care of the Partialities of thoſe which furniſh him with Memoirs, becauſe preoccupation can never
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62282:23"/> make but falſe <hi>Hiſtories. Herodotus,</hi> (whoſe
<hi>Hiſtory</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Apud <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodotum</hi> ſunt innumerabiles fabulae. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Leg.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tully</hi> condemns as fabulous) wrote only upon ill Memoirs, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> pretends.
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Marcellin.</hi> in vita
<hi>Thucyd.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Thucydides,</hi> who had a mind to mend himſelf by avoiding that fault, confines himſelf to the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of his Time, not truſting any body, in writing only what he had ſeen, or what he had learn'd from Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple worthy to be believ'd, and from <hi>Memoirs,</hi> which he collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great expences, not only from the <hi>Athenians,</hi> but alſo from the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> that he might be inform'd of both Parties. <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon, Polybius</hi> and <hi>Procopius,</hi> have done almoſt the ſame thing. <hi>Dio Caſſius</hi> confeſſes in his
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> that he had been ten years in prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the materials.
<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Saluſtius</hi> marca tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſus dicitur, ut oculis ſuis crederet de conditionibus locorum. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trare.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Petrarch</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, that
<hi>Saluſt</hi> went into <hi>Africa,</hi> that he himſelf might obſerve the Situation of the Places he was to ſpeak of in his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>War</hi> of <hi>Jugurtha,</hi> not being willing to truſt any other than his own eyes. For it is very important to be well aſſur'd of the ground you <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62282:24"/> write upon. <hi>Lucian</hi> makes the
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> of his Time paſs for a fool, who wrote the <hi>War</hi> of <hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> upon common reports, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never ſeen any body who had been in <hi>Syria,</hi> where the Battel was fought: And
<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vopiſc.</hi> in praefat.
<hi>Hiſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vopiſcus</hi> took the reſolution to write the
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the Emperour <hi>Aurelian,</hi> only upon the aſſurance that <hi>Junius Tyberianus,</hi> Miniſter of State, gave him, to furniſh him with good <hi>Records.</hi> But it is not enough to have had a ſhare in the Tranſactions of affairs; there is alſo great need of an Excellent Spirit to deliver them well.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. lib.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> 
                  <hi>Polibius</hi> ſays, that <hi>Calliſthenes</hi> was eye witneſs of the Action be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<hi>Darius</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> when he gain'd the ſtraits of
<hi>Cilicia:</hi> yet for all that, there are a great many very groſs errors in the Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that important <hi>Expedition,</hi> and all becauſe he was ignorant of the Art of <hi>War,</hi> and of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which was obſerv'd in Battels in thoſe Days. You muſt then, above all things, be very ſure of <pb n="25" facs="tcp:62282:24"/> your Matter, which ſhall never be wanting to thoſe that have Wit: but you may want aſſurance, if you do not well diſcern the things you relate. How many falſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs are found, becauſe they are ſpoil'd by People that were inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſted? though nothing is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon than Materials for <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> by reaſon that every thing may ſerve to it: We may ſay alſo, that nothing is ſcarcer than a ſufficient aſſurance of them to fit them for it: and it is hardly found, becauſe Prejudice occurs every where.
<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Boccal.</hi> in Raggual. di
<hi>Parnaſſo.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Boccaline</hi> upon that Subject de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves your eſteem, when he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes you to write nothing but what you have ſeen, and not to make it publick before you dye. That way you'r ſure of what you ſay, and there is no prejudice againſt it. But, take care above all things, to chooſe great Subjects, which can ſubſiſt upon their own ſtock: a great matter gives luſter and weight to your words; and Art muſt play in ſmall Subjects, and ſupply their weakneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62282:25"/>
               <head>VII. The Form.</head>
               <p>The Form, which ought to be given to <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> is that which is moſt eſſential to it. It is that which makes it Great or Little, and it is that from whence you take the Author's genius. You muſt then have an exalted Spirit, capable of great Idea's, if you will write well; that ſo, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Maſter of your Subject, you may give your Matter what Form you pleaſe. It is upon that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del that <hi>Livy</hi> gives to his
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> a character of greatneſs, which is beyond all other
<hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> by giving to all the Subjects he treats of, the colours their ground is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to receive. Thus he gives to the laſt Kings of
<hi>Rome</hi> all the Pride that an abſolute Authority inſpir'd them with; He changes the Spirit of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> by the auſtere Virtue of the firſt Conſuls, by the Populary Motions of the <hi>Tribunes,</hi> by the auſterity of the Government of the <hi>Decemvirs;</hi> by the lazy Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62282:25"/> of the laſt Conſuls; that he diſtinguiſhes each Age by the Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us which has been predominant in it, not confounding the different motions of that genius with the different circumſtances of Times, which don't reſemble one another, and that he ſuſtains himſelf always by the great Images he gives of the things he treats of. <hi>Tacitus</hi> to the contrary, gives almoſt to all his Matters the ſame form: all is done there by Policy; the People he ſpeaks of, have always a Spirit higher than others. It is not their Spirit which makes them move, 'tis that of the
<hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> who hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſpirit too compacted, gives always the ſame Air to his expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and the ſame turn to his thoughts<hi>:</hi> all things reſemble one another. <hi>Policy</hi> is ſtill made the cauſe and the reſult of all things.
<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tyberium</hi> aſcitum. quod ejus arroganti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am introſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerit, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratione de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrima ſibi gloriam quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiviſſe. <hi>Tacit. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Annal.</hi>
                  </note> If
<hi>Auguſtus</hi> on his death-bed choſe one to ſucceed him, he appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an <hi>Emperour</hi> worſe than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, on purpoſe that he might be mourn'd for. If
<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dolabella</hi> in abſurdam adulationem progreſſus. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Ann.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Tyberius</hi> made <hi>Piſo</hi> Governour of <hi>Syria,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:62282:26"/> 'twas only to make him a Spy to <hi>Germanicus,</hi> by whom <hi>Egypt</hi> had been govern'd, and whoſe glory he did envy.
<hi>Dolabella's</hi> flatteries diſpleas'd him, becauſe they were too courſe.
<note n="k" place="margin">Suſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat <hi>Syllam</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors ejus inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dumque ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorem inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretando. <hi>l.</hi> 13.
<hi>Annal.</hi>
                  </note> If he baniſhes <hi>Sylla,</hi> 'tis becauſe he thinks his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence a wiſe diſſimulation. That <hi>Emperour's</hi> modeſty; is nothing but a hidden Ambition; his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours are only ſnares; his mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is nothing but pride, and his Religion is nothing but grimace. He reckons it a ſign of the God's diſpleaſure, that <hi>Sejanus</hi> ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Favorite of the <hi>Emperour,</hi> and be raiſed to be a Miniſter of State. <hi>Arruntius</hi> poiſons himſelf out of Policy, that he might not fall into the hands of a maſter more brutiſh than
<hi>Tyberius.</hi> He finds an agreeableneſs even in the <hi>Emperour Claudius</hi>'s folly, and a great deal of Wit in the debauches and brutiſhneſs of <hi>Nero.</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus <hi>Neronis</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia pro in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertia fuit. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </note> Some of the
<hi>Blockheads</hi> of that <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Reign,</hi> he repreſents as men of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd Prudence. In fine, all the characters reſemble one another;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62282:26"/> Nature has no ſhare in any thing, her Sentiments are always forc'd, and every where it is the ſame genius, which reigns by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the <hi>Hiſtorian's</hi> Wit, and which has no great variety. <hi>Mariana</hi> runs on with a fuller ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer. The <hi>Romans,</hi> the <hi>Carthagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> the <hi>Arabians,</hi> the <hi>Moors,</hi> the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> make every one their Figure. The Wit of the Author mingles it ſelf only with the other Spirits, to diſtinguiſh them according to their characters, opening always ſome new way as different as the Subjects he treats of requires. We may ſay alſo, that among the <hi>Moderns,</hi> no <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory</hi> is greater for its form than that of <hi>Mariana.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>VIII. The End of Hiſtory.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Romance</hi> only pleaſes, <hi>Hiſtory</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs: This is the eſſential diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them; this ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no other end, than the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing <pb n="30" facs="tcp:62282:27"/> of the Publick.
<note n="m" place="margin">Alias in Hiſtoria leges obſervandas, alias in Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate; illa ad veritatem quaeque, in hoc ad dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctationem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferri pleraque. <hi>Cic.</hi> 1. <hi>de legib.</hi>
                  </note> For, as it is not compil'd only for the preſent; its aim ought not to be limited to the time, which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes away, but to Poſterity, which is Everlaſting. What folly were it in a Man, that ſhould think of nothing but diverting the People of the Age he lives in, when he may become uſeful to all Ages? Thoſe are the Reaſons
<note n="n" place="margin">O pulchra iſta pars, quae actiones vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamque bene format ac di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigit. <hi>Tacit. Ann. l.</hi> 3.</note>
                  <hi>Lucian</hi> uſes, to oblige an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> to think of nothing but of being uſeful, by ruling the Hearts and Minds of Men by the Inſtruction he gives them. They are deceiv'd, he ſays, who pretend that
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> can be divided into two parts, the Uſeful and Agreeable; for an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ought to have no other proſpect, than the profit People draw from a ſincere and true Narration. If he intermix ſome thing that is agreeable, he ought not to corrupt the Truth, but rather to embelliſh it, and make it the more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And, to juſtifie his Opinion, he ſhews the extravagant way of the Hiſtorians of his Age, which made
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62282:27"/> themſelves ridiculous by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other Principles.
<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Graecis</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriis plerum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que poeticae ſimilis eſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia. <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note>
                  <hi>Herodotus</hi> ſought how to pleaſe thoſe of the Age he wrote in, but his Sincerity was ſo run down in the following Ages, that it
<note n="p" place="margin">Et quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid <hi>Graecia</hi> mendax pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat in Hiſtoria. <hi>Juv. Sat.</hi> 10.</note> made the Sincerity of the
<hi>Greek Hiſtorians</hi> be ſuſpected in <hi>Quintilian</hi>'s Time.
<hi>Photius</hi> makes mention of an <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> which thought that his ſaying incredible things made him the more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. And
<note n="q" place="margin">Quidam incredibilium relatu com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendationem parant: &amp; Lectorem ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud acturum, ſi per quotidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na duceretur, miraculo exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; &amp; opus ſuum fieri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulare non putant, niſi mendacio a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſerint, <hi>Sen. l.</hi> 7. <hi>quaeſt. Nat.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> complains, that in his Time there were
<hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> who pretended to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves famous by their fabulous Narrations. This was always plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to the People who delight in Fictions; but not to Men of Senſe and Honeſty, who love Truth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. In the following Ages, the <hi>Arabians</hi> ſtuff'd their Writings with ſo many Fables, that they ſpoil'd the greateſt part of the <hi>Greek Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> of their Age, by the fancy then in faſhion, of mingling ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing Adventures in all their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations: they thought the only way to pleaſe the People, was to ſay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible things. The ſame Spirit
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62282:28"/> infected part of the <hi>Modern Graecians,</hi> which is the cauſe why the Account we have of thoſe Times by the <hi>By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zantine Hiſtory,</hi> is not the ſureſt in the World, the Authors of it not ſeeming very exact; and when an Author writes by their Memoirs, he ought to take great Precautions againſt ſo falſe an Idea, to make People believe him, becauſe the leaſt falſhood ſpoils all, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts Truth into a Fable. Even the trueſt things ought not to be told, when they appear incredible or extraordinary, unleſs you give 'em an appearance, or, at leaſt, a colour of Truth. It is what <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydides</hi> does: and, though he ſaw <hi>Herodotus</hi> in ſo great an eſteem, that the names of the
<hi>Muſes</hi> were given to his Books, he thought of nothing but of ſpeaking the <hi>Truth,</hi> without minding to pleaſe the People.
<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lucian.</hi> de conſer. Hiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>I had rather,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>pleaſe by telling Truth, than be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in telling Tales: becauſe, if I be not pleaſant, I may be uſeful; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, I might do hurt in being agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Utilitatem juvandi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulerunt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae placendi. <hi>Plin. praef. Hiſt. Nat.</hi> de <hi>Thucyd.</hi> &amp; al. Hiſt.</note> Be then ſtrongly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62282:28"/> that nothing is fine in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> but that which is real; and that,
<hi>Truth</hi> being its greateſt Ornament, an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> that will pleaſe, ought to ſpeak true.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>IX. That Truth is the only mean through which Hiſtory comes to its end: and how it is to be found.</head>
               <p>Truth being the only mean by which <hi>Hiſtory</hi> can ſurely inſtruct; Truth ought to make the chiefeſt Rule of Hiſtory, as your <hi>Hiſtory</hi> ought to be the ground of People's <hi>Belief.</hi> But where is it to be found? Is there any thing in the World more hidden than Truth? For, beſides the Clouds ſhe is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encompaſs'd with, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her ſometimes unacceſſible, ſhe is wrap'd up with all the Diſguiſes men's imaginations are capable of. And if the ordinary ignorance of ſhort-ſighted Writers is an obſtacle to the knowledge of Truth; their little ſincerity, nay, their fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous way, is a far greater. For how often do we give wrong Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, through falſe Idea's which ariſe from our Paſſion, Intereſt, or <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62282:29"/> Prejudice, which Error or Opinion are wont to inſpire Men's minds? In fine, Truth being of a nature ſo unknown to Men, either through her own obſcurity, or through the weakneſs of their Underſtanding, or for want of application; there is nothing harder than to make her known to the Publick with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out defacing her. And, as ſhe is continually corrupted, and even prophan'd, through the baſeneſs of her Adorers, the moſt part of the <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> being commonly Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of Courts<hi>:</hi> You ought to ſet your ſelf above hope or fear, as ſoon as you meddle with writing, that you may always dare to ſay the Truth. But, it is not enough to have a mind to ſay it, you muſt alſo make your ſelf able, by ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in its pureſt original, by ſearching the Cloſets of the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and curious, and by conſulting the Inſtructions of thoſe who have had a ſhare in buſineſſes, to unra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel what has been moſt myſterious in the moſt private intrigues.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:62282:29"/> You muſt, above all things, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Men in general; to diſcover their Spirit, to dive into their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, to know the greateſt weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their hearts, to penetrate their very thoughts, that you may not impoſe falſe ones upon them; and to judge of them by thoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and unforeſeen Motions, which ſlip from them without their notice. That way you may diſcover the true ſentiments of the Soul; the heart having no ſpare time to obſerve it ſelf and to put on a diſguiſe<hi>:</hi> for as ſoon as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects, it forces it ſelf, as
<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Agrippinae</hi> pavor &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternatio mentis emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis vultu pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meretur. <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> quamvis rudibus annis, dolorem, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem, affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus omnes ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcondere didi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerat. Ita poſt breve ſilenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um repetita convivii laeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.
<hi>Tacit. l.</hi> 13. <hi>Ann.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tacitus</hi> obſerves in
<hi>Agrippa,</hi> and in <hi>Octavia</hi> Siſter to <hi>Britannicus.</hi> For, in the moment that the poiſon which <hi>Nero</hi> ſent him at the Banquet at which he died, ſeis'd his Spirits; <hi>Octavia,</hi> as well as
<hi>Agrippina</hi> ſhew'd Conſternation in their faces: But, as
<hi>Octavia</hi> thought to marry <hi>Nero,</hi> and <hi>Agrippina</hi> his Mother; a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man naturally proud, had a mind to Reign, upon a politick Account they reſum'd their Countenance; and that they might not anger the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62282:30"/> Emperour, who was making ſure of his Rival to the Empire; they force their Sentiments, hide their Sorrows, and continue their Supper with the ſame mirth, (whilſt the Prince was expiring in the Antichamber) as if nothing had paſs'd of that kind. There is a great Spirit in that Author, whoſe deſign is, to give an exact knowledg of thoſe whoſe <hi>Hiſtory</hi> he writes. But, our late Authors think but little of that, and that is the reaſon why we have ſo few true <hi>Hiſtorians.</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Rerum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciator ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerus <hi>Thucydi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Cic. de Clar. Orat.</hi>
                  </note> There is a Temper of mind, fit to ſay things as they are, which is not a common one. It is one of the properties of <hi>Thucydides,</hi> the moſt faithful and ſincere of all <hi>Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> There is in his Works a Taſt of Truth, and a diſcerning of Truth from Falſhood, join'd to an exact Spirit, which acquir'd him the approbation and eſteem of all people.
<note n="w" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dionyſ Halyc.</hi> in Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio de
<hi>Thucyd.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Dionyſius Haly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnaſſaeus</hi> praiſes him above all for his ſticking to the Truth, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that he never ſaid any thing againſt his Conſcience; in <pb n="37" facs="tcp:62282:30"/> which he has excell'd
<hi>Herodotus,</hi> whoſe whole deſign was to pleaſe People: for
<hi>Strabo</hi> ſays, that he mingles Fables with his <hi>Hiſtories</hi> on purpoſe to render them agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.
<note n="x" place="margin">Scribe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curus, dicas quod velis, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biturus men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciorum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites quos hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriae elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiae mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur authores. <hi>Vopiſc. praefaet. Hiſt.</hi>
                  </note> The <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> of the Low Empire became ſo great Flaterers, that their want of Sincerity made <hi>Vopiſcus</hi> change the mind he had of writing the
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> of his Time. But, the Governour of the Town, who was a Favorite of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, took off that Scruple, in a Diſcourſe he had with him, as they were once walking together, by ſhewing him, that the greateſt <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> had been deceiv'd in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things.
<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſin. Poll.</hi> apud Florid. Sab.</note> 
                  <hi>Pollio</hi> tells us, that the ſame thing had happen'd to
<hi>Caeſar</hi> in his <hi>Commentarys,</hi> for not having review'd his writings. If the greateſt men are ſubject to err, what will ordinary ones do?
<note n="z" place="margin">Neminem Scriptorum, quantum ad Hiſtoriam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet, non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid eſle men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titum. <hi>Vopiſc. ibid.</hi>
                  </note> And if Truth does not always ſhew it ſelf in its purity to extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Spirits, how will it make it ſelf known to ſmall ones, who, through the quality of their <hi>Genius,</hi> can ſay nothing without altering <pb n="38" facs="tcp:62282:31"/> the Circumſtances, by diminiſhing or inlarging the objects? for there is nothing ſcarcer than an exact temper, fit to ſay things as they are: we ſay them as we conceive 'em; and we conceive
'em good or bad, according as our Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is<hi>:</hi> and, of many that have ſeen the ſame thing, there is not often above two that relates it alike, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſaying what he has ſeen, according to the Idea he has conceiv'd of it, and as his mind is turn'd. The quality then, I ſay, moſt requiſite for an <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> is a Spirit exact and faithful, in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Truth in all its Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, ſo as to deſerve the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's belief. But it is not enough for an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> to ſay what is true, he muſt give it alſo a fine turn: that turn is the Style; let us ſee which is the moſt Convenient for <hi>Hiſtory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:62282:31"/>
               <head>X. The Style fit for Hiſtory.</head>
               <p>The Style is the Form of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and the manner you write in: the fitteſt for every body is that which is moſt comformable to his genius, which ought to be follow'd, without forcing it; ſo that a Style mixt is always vicious. It is a defect of <hi>Strada</hi> in his
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the Low Country's, who by the clearneſs of his Imagination, and by his great Lectures, had fill'd his mind with different characters; and that mixture which is found in his manner of writing, how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable ſoever it is, diminiſhes its Perfection.
<note n="a" place="margin">Verum ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum inſcriben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſinceritate candoreque elucet. <hi>Melch. Can. in loc. Theol. l.</hi> 11.
<hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Mariana,</hi> who was of the ſame Society, has more ſtrength, and is ſmoother in his Style. But the fitteſt Style for
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> is that which has moſt of the Character of Truth, and wherein that natural light of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, which commonly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies the Truth, ſhines moſt<hi>:</hi> for, people eaſily believe things di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted thus.
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> de conſer.
<hi>Hiſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The Style for</hi> 
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:62282:32"/>
                  <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> as <hi>Lucian</hi> ſays, <hi>muſt be clean and natural, becauſe that clearneſs is the Rule of what it ought to ſay, as Truth is a Rule of what it ought to think.</hi> Its
<note n="c" place="margin">Quanquam vincta ſit, ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta videri debet oratio. <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> Diſcourſe muſt be free, though well compacted, and that it may have that freedom which makes it natural, it requires leſs number than Turn.
<note n="d" place="margin">Hiſtoria non tam fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos numeros, quam orbem contextum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que deſiderat. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </note> But becauſe an
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ought to read ancient Authors, to make himſelf a Style according to his capacity, he ſhall find it neceſſary to make his Obſervations in that Study, and ſo form to himſelf a Method fit for his Deſign.
<note n="e" place="margin">In <hi>Herodoto</hi> omnia leniter fluunt: tum ipſa dialectus habet jucundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem. <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 9.
<hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Herodotus</hi>'s Style is ſweet, flowing, and agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. That of
<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Thucydides</hi> praeſractior, nec ita rotun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. In eo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem orationis deſidero. <hi>Cic.</hi> in <hi>Bruto.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Thucydides</hi> is nobler and greater, but not ſo natural; he has a rough way, which makes him obſcure, and he has leſs num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and leſs turn than
<hi>Herodotus.</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Obſcurus
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t quia preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.
<hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Xenophon</hi> has a tender and ſweet ſtrain. His Diſcourſe, which is not unlike to pure and clear Water, has no fellow in
<hi>Antiquity,</hi> except <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s; for nothing was ever writ in
<hi>Latin</hi> more clearly.
<note n="h" place="margin">Tribus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris de bello civili
<hi>Caeſari</hi> falſo aſcriptis nihil durius, nec candori
<hi>Caeſariano</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus conveniens <hi>Flor. Sabin.</hi> in <hi>calum. long. lat.</hi>
                  </note> A Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Crtick's obſervation (who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62282:32"/> ſome difference of Style in his Book of the Civil Wars, which he pretends to have not been written ſo purely as the Wars of the
<hi>Gaules</hi>) goes beyond me<hi>:</hi> I have not knowledge enough to find that, and I am of <hi>Sueto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>'s Mind, who makes no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference throughout. I confeſs I am delighted with the Eloquence and Simplicity of that Author, no body ever wrote more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
<note n="i" place="margin">Genus ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is fuſum &amp; cum lenitate quadam a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili profluens, ſine judiciali aſperitate, &amp; Sententiarum forentium acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leis proſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. <hi>Cic. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de Orat.</hi>
                  </note> but the Nobleneſs of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi>'s Diſcourſe charm my Spirits. That <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> has been read with reſpect in all Nations, for almoſt now two thouſand years, upon the ſcore of that Majeſtick way of ſpeaking, which has been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd by all Ages. Nothing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo fills my Fancy better than that admirable choice of Words al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways fitted to his Sentiments, and that expreſſing of Sentiments al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways conformable to the things he Speaks of. In a word, he is the Man of all, that has better attain'd to that Style <hi>Cicero</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes one to follow in
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> 
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:62282:33"/> And 'tis by that great Model that
<hi>Mariana, Buchanan, Paulus Aemili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Paulus Jovius,</hi> and all thoſe who carried any Vogue after their Age, have formed themſelves in the way of Writing <hi>Hiſtory. Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> is not ſo fit; for that Luſtre of his high flights is like Lightning, whoſe Brightneſs dazels, inſtead of making the Matter plain. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terculus</hi> and <hi>Florus</hi> have given a ſmall Air, flouriſh'd and delicate, which pleaſes their <hi>Readers.</hi> The Writers <hi>Auguſtae Hiſtoriae,</hi> as <hi>Ammi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus Marcellinus, Lampridius, Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus, Julius Capitolius, Vopiſcus,</hi> and the others, have degenerated in a cold and impure Style, which has nothing of that Noble Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of former Ages.
<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Saluſtius</hi> rerum Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. <hi>Tac. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Hiſt.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Saluſt</hi> is great and elevate in his way of Writing, which cauſes
<hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian</hi> to compare him to <hi>Thucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dides.</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Saluſtio</hi> vigente ampu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatae Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, &amp; obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra brevitas fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere pro cultu. <hi>Sen. l.</hi> 11.
<hi>Epiſt.</hi> 114.</note> 
                  <hi>Q. Curtius</hi> has a poliſh'd and bright Style. And by thoſe two Methods, which are almoſt the only two fit to be uſed, you may examine which of the two is the fitteſt for
<hi>Hiſtory;</hi> and that <pb n="43" facs="tcp:62282:33"/> Queſtion is the moſt important that can be made upon that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>XI. Which is the propereſt for Hiſtory, the Great or the flouriſh'd Style?</head>
               <p>In a Queſtion of ſo great a Conſequence as this, which is not yet determined; 'tis enough for one to give the Reaſons which may ſerve for the deciſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, when a Man has not the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of determining it.
<note n="m" place="margin">Verba ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerpſit <hi>Saluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ex origini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Catonis. <hi>Suet.</hi> in <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſt</hi> has a Greatneſs in his Style; but ſome of his Expreſſions are harſh, which makes him look dry in ſome Places, becauſe he had form'd himſelf by the rudeneſs
<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Saluſtius</hi> Scriptor ſeriae et ſeverae ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis. <hi>Aulug. l.</hi> 17. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</note> of the Remains of <hi>Cato;</hi> which gives to his <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> a Gravity which looks like Severity. And contrariwiſe, none is more poliſh'd than
<hi>Q. Curtius;</hi> It is an <hi>admirable</hi> Flower of
<hi>Expreſſion,</hi> which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Men of Wit, but the buſineſs is, that we muſt examin whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſtiff Stile of <hi>Saluſt,</hi> hard as it is, be not wholſomer and fitter for <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> giving as it does
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62282:34"/> Weight, Strength, and Greatneſs to the
<hi>Diſcourſe.</hi> Is it not rich? and don't we find ſometimes in that hard and ſevere Stile, that agreeableneſs of which <hi>Demetrius</hi> the
<hi>Phalerian</hi> ſpeaks; which
<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Homer.</hi> Odyſſ. <hi>l.</hi>
9.</note> 
                  <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> has ſo well expreſs'd in his
<hi>Odyſſaea,</hi> about the Adventures of <hi>Polyphemus;</hi> where
<hi>Demetrius</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, in his Book of <hi>Elocution,</hi> that he is the firſt <hi>Author</hi> of it; that is to ſay, thoſe Graces which have nothing ſoft nor effeminate, and which are agreeable without being affected. The ſame <hi>Author</hi> quotes many Examples of it, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of
<hi>Xenophon,</hi> who has the Art of making things Pleaſant, which of themſelves are not at all ſo. Herein that ſevere Stile properly conſiſts, which
<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hermogen.</hi> de Ideis, <hi>l.</hi>
1. <hi>c.</hi> 5. &amp; <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>de invent.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenes</hi> prefers to a ſoft Stile, when he ſays, that a meer naked <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> has often more Strength, than a Narration which is adorn'd and flouriſh'd; becauſe a ſevere Style may have ſome Greatneſs, and a ſoft Style can only have a <hi>Mediocrity.</hi> That is alſo the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <pb n="45" facs="tcp:62282:34"/> why he reckons good Senſe, (tho' never ſo naked) amongſt the qualities of the Noble and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated Style. This was, ſays he, the Character of <hi>Pericles,</hi> upon which
<hi>Demoſthenes</hi> form'd himſelf to that ſtrong and fierce
<hi>Eloquence,</hi> wherein he has excell'd<hi>: Hiperides,</hi> ſays he, in another place, is great tho' careleſs: his Style is rough and dry, but it is noble and elevate;
<note n="q" place="margin">Auſterus graeca conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine
<hi>Cornal. Fron. de differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocum.</hi>
                  </note> for, that <hi>Auſterity</hi> of Stile, which was the true Character of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> is nothing but
<note n="r" place="margin">Artis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verae ſi quis amat effectus, mentemque magnis appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, prius mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re frugalitatis lege polleat exacta. <hi>Pet.</hi>
                  </note> a true and exact Senſe, and a juſt and correct Reaſon; which, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtopping at a ſhew of Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, purſues
<hi>Solidity.</hi>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Si juvenes verba atroci ſtylo effode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, jam illa grandis oratio haberet maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis ſuas pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.
<hi>Petr.</hi>
                  </note> It has nothing falſe in its Sentiments; all its Attention is bent towards a Sobriety of <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> which is nothing but Senſe and Simplicity. <hi>Plutarch</hi> alſo attributes that Style to <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> which <hi>Dionyſius Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycarnaſſaeus</hi> does not diſtinguiſh from the great and elevate. It is, in fine, that ſtrength of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, which alone gives to our
<hi>Diſcourſe, Nobleneſs</hi> and <hi>Majeſty,</hi> by
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62282:35"/> which it becomes great and ſolid. Hence it is that
<hi>Caeſar,</hi> thô un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected, has ſomething <hi>Nobler</hi> in the Simplicity of his <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> than <hi>Tacitus</hi> with all the <hi>Pomp</hi> of his Words: and there appears a kind of
<hi>Careleſneſs</hi> in the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents,</hi> which is worth all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of the <hi>Moderns.</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Hiſtorica locutio, ubi munditiem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuerit, majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ornamenta non requirat, ſimplex, pura, naturalis ſit, nec Atticum ſiccitatem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre poſſit. <hi>Beni. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Hiſt.</hi>
                  </note> I don't ſay, but that a flouriſh'd Style may be of uſe in ſmall <hi>Hiſtories,</hi> which have not ground enough to ſupport themſelves without help.
<note n="u" place="margin">It is a ſmall Hiſtory in French.</note> The <hi>Princeſs</hi> of <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſier</hi> ought to be written with all the <hi>Eloquence</hi> Art can allow; but the
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the War of <hi>Paris,</hi> and of the Late Troubles, ought to be written with a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Air; Small Subjects require Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery, great Ones Strength and Dignity. Let <hi>Paterculus</hi> be pretti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adorn'd in the Character he took; but <hi>Livy</hi> ought to be great and ſerious: ſmall
<hi>Beauties</hi> ought to be finely attir'd to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but great ones have no need of it, becauſe they bear a good weight of themſelves. Beſides, <pb n="47" facs="tcp:62282:35"/> Truth, which is the Soul of
<hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi> becomes ſuſpicious, as ſoon as it is too much adorned; and Careleſneſs has more an Air of Sincerity. This is what was to be obſerved upon the Style in particular, after the general No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions I have given thereof: but as it is of uſe only in <hi>Narration,</hi> we'll
<hi>examine</hi> in what manner it ought to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>XII. The Narration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hiſtory</hi> being, properly ſpeaking, nothing but a
<note n="w" place="margin">Hiſtoria eſt narratio rei geſtae, per quam ea quae facta ſunt dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcuntur. <hi>Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. l.</hi> 1.
<hi>Orig.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Rehearſal</hi> of things paſt, and in the ſame order as they came to paſs, ought alſo to be a continued
<hi>Narration.</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Expoſitio praeteritorum Temporum.
<hi>Fab. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as it hath nothing more eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial than the knowing how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late well, ſo, nothing is more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult.
<note n="y" place="margin">Cuſtodia fidelis rerum geſtarum.
<hi>Tit. Liv. l.</hi> 6. <hi>Annal.</hi>
                  </note> For it is a great Art to fix an unconſtant and fickle <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>'s mind. What <hi>wiſdom</hi> does it not require to mannage every where thoſe colours that are neceſſary to give the reſemblance to things, and to mix conſtantly with them
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62282:36"/> thoſe features, thoſe light touches, thoſe graces, that warmth, that quickneſs, which hinders a Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from languiſhing? how dexterous muſt an Hiſtorian be, to uſe both Art and Wit, in what he ſays, yet not to ſeem to do ſo;
<note n="z" place="margin">Dare ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis varios vultus. gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent enim res varietate. <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> And by all the variety of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, Figures and Thoughts, to adorn every part of his
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> without the leaſt ſmatch of Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation? what knowledg ought he to have, to diſcern what muſt be ſaid, and what let alone, to ſpeak and hold his Peace, to dwell no longer than is fit upon the Points he treats of; to explain things at large, or by degrees, as neceſſity or a good <hi>Decorum</hi> requires; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large or ſhorten them; to retrench, by a felicity of Expreſſion, thoſe <hi>Topicks,</hi> which otherwiſe would be inſipid, and never to weary the Reader by too great an uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? In fine, what a Judgment to ſeparate carefully that which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming from that which is not Decent? for upon that chiefly runs all the Beauty of a Narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <pb n="49" facs="tcp:62282:36"/> and all the Grace of
<hi>Hiſtory.</hi> But a Narration is perfect when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it has nothing of Superflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. This is, in a word, the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt perfection it is capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought to. The Rules lay'd down by <hi>Cicero</hi> and
<note n="a" place="margin">Circumciſa expoſitio rei quae ſuperva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuis caret. <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>
                  <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſay no more: after them I have nothing to ſay. For when once the Superfluities are cut off, the Circumlocutions which are not uſeful, the feigned <hi>Deſcriptions</hi> which are onely fit to make a ſhew, and all the vain Ornaments of the Diſcourſe are ſuppreſs'd, every thing comes cloſe to its point.
<note n="b" place="margin">Denſus, brevis, ſemper inſtans ſibi co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatis affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. <hi>Thucydi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Fab. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi>
1.</note> The Vigour, the Strength and the Dignity, all ſupport each other, without any Flatneſs. In that
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Thucydides</hi> verbis aptus &amp; preſſus. <hi>Cic. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de Orat.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Thucydides</hi> out-did <hi>Horedotus,</hi> who is too big in ſome places, where he gives himſelf too much to the fineneſs of his Imagination.
<note n="d" place="margin">Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem illam <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtis</hi> velocita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem conſequu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus <hi>Livius. Fab. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>
                  <hi>Saluſt</hi> is of a Character exact and ſhort. He is properly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable for the quickneſs and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of his Diſcourſe.
<note n="e" place="margin">Illa <hi>Saluſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> brevitas, qua nihil apud aures erudiras perfectius eſſe poteſt, captan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.
<hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </note> That is it which animates him, and makes him ſo lively.
<hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <pb n="50" facs="tcp:62282:37"/> is admirable for its Purity and Eloquence, but it is not quick enough; and he wants of that Strength which he found too abounding in <hi>Terence.</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Livius</hi> in narrando mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra jucundita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, clariſſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que candoris, ita ducuntur omnia tum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, tum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonis accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modata. <hi>Fab. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> As for
<hi>Livy,</hi> he has a way of reherſing that is very taking, by that Art he has of mixing in his Narration ſmall things with great ones; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe great ones, when too much enlarg'd, tire the Reader by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great Attention they require, and ſmall ones refreſh him<hi>:</hi> it is with that ſame Method that he varies his Adventures; that he interchanges ſad things for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful ones; that Mannages his Light and his Shade with a wiſe and judicious Temper, that ſo he may keep the <hi>Reader</hi> in tune by that <hi>Variety.</hi> For a <hi>Narration</hi> becomes inſipid, as ſoon as it wants diverſity of Accidents, Adventures, Figures, and Expreſſions. You muſt even allow ſome intervals to things, that your Reader may take breath, and not intermix your matter by too great a confuſion of things. It is a fault that <hi>Dionyſius Haly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnaſſaeus</hi> 
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:62282:37"/> judges
<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Thucydides</hi> creber rerum frequentia. <hi>Cic. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de Orat.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Thucydides</hi> guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, in the third Book of his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, where he ſo mixes the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Intereſts
<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dionyſius Halyc.</hi> tractat.
<hi>de judic. Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyd.</hi>
                  </note> of the <hi>Athenians, Lacedemonians,</hi> and of the other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Greece,</hi> that he confounds, in a manner, the very appearance of things, by a Narration too much loaded with Matter: and this fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure is incident to thoſe of a copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and fluent Invention. Tho' the
<note n="i" place="margin">Rerum ratio ordinem temporum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat. <hi>Cic. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de Orat.</hi>
                  </note> order of Times be the moſt natural to a Narration, becauſe it unfolds things paſs'd; there is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs an order of Reaſon in ranging <hi>Events,</hi> which ought par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to be the ſtudy of an <hi>Hiſtorian.</hi> It is only by that ſecret Order that you may endear your Reader, ſo as to imprint your own Sentiments on his Mind, when you ſhew him Men acting naturally as they ought: and when you ſhew him their Manners, their Thoughts, their Deſigns and their Motives, as they are in a kind of dependency upon each other in the ſame natural order, which joyns them well together, <pb n="52" facs="tcp:62282:38"/>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">In rebus magnis, memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riaque dignis, confilia pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, deinde act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, poſtea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventus expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantur, <hi>Cic.</hi> l. 2. de Orat.</note> An
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> that can well put thoſe things together, is a great Man; that is the thing which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and not thoſe extraordinary Events which People run after for want for Judgment; for nothing is more taking than to ſee men act in that Order; that alone, when all comes to all, fixes the mind.
<hi>Livy</hi> excell'd in that, becauſe he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd cloſely that Order, by draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Thread of his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> with a connexion of Diſcourſe, and by weaving together always thoſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that are of an equal ſize.
<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Longin.</hi> c. 18.</note>
                  <hi>Longinus</hi> has well obſerved, that <hi>Thucydides</hi> breaks the Order of things, to ſurprize the Reader by that diſorder, by bringing in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected Occurrences in his Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: He tells even ſometimes things paſt in the preſent time, ſhewing them as thô they were paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing actually, which makes the Reader more attentive, and affects him moſt. <hi>Tacitus</hi> is of a ſoaring Spirit, who does not ſay things in order. His great ſenſe, ſhut up in the compaſs of a few words, has not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62282:38"/> an extent proportioned to his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's minds, who are often over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with it<hi>:</hi> and having not a natural ſtrain in what he ſays, he ſcarce ever fits his words to mens Notions; he does not inſtruct well: For Example, when on the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Papian Law</hi> he explains the ground of the Laws; or in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place, he ſpeaks of <hi>Aſylums,</hi> he does not return to the origin of things; he ſhews nothing clearly, or he does it ill; as when he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> l. 5. of his <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> his very Style is not fir for it, which is a great fault in an <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> whoſe chiefeſt Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is to inſtruct. After all, a Narration is good (which way ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is digeſted) when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>XIII. Tranſitions.</head>
               <p>The great Art of a Narration, and one of its chiefeſt Beauties, conſiſts in the Tranſitions. In ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, thoſe fine and natural turns, <pb n="54" facs="tcp:62282:39"/> thoſe happy paſſages from one Subject to another, make the ſtream of a Diſcourſe engaging: thoſe inſinuating ways lead the mind of a Reader from one Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to another, and ſhew him a great deal, without tiring him<hi>:</hi> In fine, all that admirable Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy of the Tranſition, is that which is moſt delicate and ſpritely in the Narration, which ſeem al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways conſtrain'd, and never eaſie or natural without that Art. It is not enough to ſpeak well to attain it: you muſt be eloquent; you muſt be Maſter of your Subject, and to know the grounds and conſequences well; for the fitteſt Tranſitions ought to be much more in things than in words. So that thoſe Excurſions from Kingdom to Kingdom, from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Nation, from Age to Age, without Method, and without Management, are no way op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune to a well digeſted
<hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> wherein all things ought to be well laid and compacted; as in a great <hi>Palace,</hi> where nothing <pb n="55" facs="tcp:62282:39"/> ought to be ſcatter'd or irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; for the compactneſs, and the proportion of its Apartments, make one of its greateſt Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties<hi>:</hi> So
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> is like a Body, compos'd of its Members by the Natural Union; in which <hi>Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>'s Hiſtory of the <hi>Schiſm</hi> of
<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is very defective, amongſt Moderns, as that of
<hi>Florus</hi> and <hi>Paterculus,</hi> amongſt the Ancients.
<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon</hi> fluens &amp; fine ſalebris oratio, <hi>Cic.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Xenophon</hi>'s Language is very well knit, ſweet and flowing, yet <hi>Livy</hi> ſtill exceeds him, his Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration being of one even conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued thread; his Tranſitions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt leſs in words than in things. <hi>Saluſt</hi> is not ſo well knit;
<hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> is ſtill leſs; his Connexions are forc'd, and the ſtréam of his Diſcourſe much interrupted, which ſurprizes the Reader, who muſt ſweat, if he will follow that Author. The moſt difficult Tranſitions are thoſe which are found in the commoneſt things; for an Author ought to ſuſtain himſelf with ſtrong Expreſſions, where the matter is but ſmall, <pb n="56" facs="tcp:62282:40"/> and muſt find a way how to couple things that otherwiſe have no Union at all. It is in thoſe places he ought to ſhew all his Skill. The Reader's mind is ſo tender, that an
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> cannot always turn it as he pleaſes. But he muſt be conducted from ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to adventure, by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexions well cover'd for Order's ſake. For, in a word, he often has a fooliſh pride, and flights, which render him untractable. But there is need of a great deal of Art to vary thoſe Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, which never ought to be like one another, to give always new Ideas to the Reader, by not ſhewing him always the ſame Objects<hi>:</hi> It is in this an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> muſt lay out his Induſtry; for herein the gracefulneſs of a Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration conſiſts, which alone can render it acceptable and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:62282:40"/>
               <head>XIV. The Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of a Narration.</head>
               <p>If a Narration becomes agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the Tranſitions, it be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>comes credible by the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. For nothing engages one more than a Fact cloath'd with good Circumſtances, which thô dark and obſcure of it ſelf, by the particulars becomes palpable, clear, ſenſible and evident; and as the progreſs of great under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, and of Affairs of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, is ſeen only by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into a good order by the ſeveral degrees of their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; ſo the Art of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining the Truth in all its De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendencies, by unravelling what is particular, making one of the great Ornaments of <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> a Writer ought to ſtudy it with all imaginable care. Here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the Obſervations one may make of it. The great Secret is, to know how to make a wiſe and judicious choice of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances <pb n="58" facs="tcp:62282:41"/> that are capable of giving a great Idea of things, to imprint in them that Colour which can give them credit, and ſo make way for them to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the mind. And this will be obtain'd by a concourſe of great and ſmall Circumſtances mixt with Dexterity, when well cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. Great Circumſtances give ſome admiration, and ſmall ones pleaſure, provided they are well choſen, and not exaggerated. But thô an Action, which is not exactly reported, makes no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, you muſt nevertheleſs ſhun thoſe Expreſſions of low and frivolous Particulars, which make a Subject worſe; for you become childiſh, and even ridiculous, by ſticking too cloſe to little things; As that impertinent Hiſtorian
<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> in Conſer. Hiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Lucian</hi> ſpeaks of, who gives a very particular Deſcription of the <hi>Parthian</hi>'s Veſte, and of the <hi>Roman Emperour</hi>'s Shield, when he deſcribes the Fight. Others, adds he, not thinking of Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al things, loſe time in things not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62282:41"/> uſeful; as he, who after having ſpoke by the by, a word or two of the <hi>Battel,</hi> which made then the Subject of his Diſcourſe, ſtops to relate the Adventures of a <hi>Mooriſh</hi> Knight, the moſt extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant in the World. So <hi>Proco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius,</hi> in his ſecret
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> forgets the Circumſtances neceſſary, and rehearſes what is needleſs. You muſt then, in the recital of any Action of Conſequence, know well how to lay the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which are to make the thing plain, and to ſuſtain it in its light, by diſtinguiſhing the Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial from that which is not ſo. The moſt accompliſht pattern we have in <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of a great Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, told in all the Circumſtances capable of giving it weight and ſplendor, is <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s March in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<hi>Italy,</hi> as it is written in the 21<hi>ſt</hi> Book of the Annals of
<hi>Livy.</hi> It is, in my judgment, the moſt perfect part of his
<hi>Hiſtory;</hi> and there are few things of that ſtrength in Antiquity. A greater deſign never enter'd into a more <pb n="60" facs="tcp:62282:42"/> extraordinary mind; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was ever accompliſh't more cleverly. The Argument was,
<hi>Hannibal</hi>'s coming out of <hi>Africa,</hi> marching through
<hi>Spain,</hi> over the <hi>Pyrenean Hills;</hi> croſſing the
<hi>Rhone,</hi> at his very mouth, a <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> vaſt and ſwift, whoſe Banks were cover'd with ſo many E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; his opening himſelf a way through the <hi>Alpes,</hi> where no man had ever paſs'd before; travelling upon <hi>Precipices;</hi> diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at every ſtep with People that lay in Ambuſcadoes, in continual Filings, amidſt the Snow, Ice, Rain, Torrents, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Storms and Thunder; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king War with Heaven, Earth, and all the Elements; drawing after him an Army of a hundred thouſand Men of different Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all jealous of a General, whoſe Courage they were not able to imitate. The Souldiers Minds were poſſeſt with fear, <hi>Hannibal</hi> alone remains unſhaken, the danger which encompaſſes him, abates the Courage of all <pb n="61" facs="tcp:62282:42"/> the Army, but never diſturbs his Mind. All is drawn in a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of horrid Circumſtances; in every word of that
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is expreſt; never Picture was better finiſh'd in Hiſtory, touch'd with livelier Colours, and with bolder ſtrokes. Nothing alſo is better adorned with Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in
<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tacit.</hi> l. 2.
<hi>Annal.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tacitus,</hi> than that Feaſt the Empreſs
<hi>Meſſalina</hi> made to ſhew her Love to <hi>Silius,</hi> her Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant. All the Ceremonies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd as thô it had been Vintage-time, that Seaſon favouring the Feaſt; Mirth, Pleaſure, frolick and laſcivious Debauchery, are all expreſs'd with the fineneſs of an exquiſite Eloquence; and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation thereof is particulariz'd ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly and ſenſibly, and made throughout in ſuch a manner, as ſpeaks Life and Spirit; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more judiciouſly plac'd, rendring by this lively repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation <hi>Meſſalina</hi>'s Death, which follows after more Tragical and full of Horror. In fine, there are happy Circumſtances, which <pb n="62" facs="tcp:62282:43"/> give an agreeableneſs every where, where they are apply'd; but you muſt underſtand them well, to know where they muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd. Things become often grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by their Circumſtances, than they do by themſelves. Let us then look into thoſe Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which can both inſtruct and pleaſe, and keep the Reader from doazing. Let us imitate <hi>Davila,</hi> who is ſo taking, by the Art he has duly to cloath what he ſays with proper Circumſtances; yet great Relations weary the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; ſo let us make a judicious diſtinction of the Circumſtances Neceſſary, and of Importance, from thoſe that are not ſo. Let us conſult <hi>Lucian,</hi> and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon Hiſtory; he is a great Maſter in that. But to make a compleat Narration, we muſt joyn to the Circumſtances of its things, the Motives of its Actions; for Motives well touch'd make a Narration as curious, as the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances make it likely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:62282:43"/>
               <head>XV. The Motives.</head>
               <p>To tell Men's Actions without ſpeaking of their Motives, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not properly be called to write <hi>Hiſtory.</hi> It is juſt like a
<hi>Gazette,</hi> where the Author contents him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf barely to report the Events of things, without going up to their Spring. As <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who gives meerly his Marches, and his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campings, without telling their Motives; every thing in his Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration being too plain and open; thô 'tis true he writes only Memoirs. It is then that curious rehearſing of Motives which cauſe Men to Act, by which alone <hi>Hiſtory</hi> it ſelf becomes delicate, and ſuſtains it ſelf chiefly in important Affairs. To ſay things as they are paſs'd, without going to their beginning, is properly to ſtop at the outward part of Things. <hi>Reaſon will have it,</hi> ſays Cicero,
<note n="p" place="margin">Rerum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio vult, ut quoniam in rebus magnis confilia pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, deinde acta, poſtea eventus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectantur; in rebus geſtis declarari, non ſolum quid actum, aut dictum ſit, ſed quomodo, &amp; cum de eventu dicatur, ut cauſae explicentur omnes, &amp;c. <hi>l.</hi>
2. <hi>de Orat.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that as in Affairs,</hi> 
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:62282:44"/>
                  <hi>the Deſign precedes the Execution; The Historian gives an Account, not only of Events, but alſo of Cauſes; and that in relating what has been done, he explains how, and for what Reaſon it was done. Tacitus</hi> ſays al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the ſame thing; that it is important for <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> not only to tell the Events of things, but to diſcover the Ground and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of them, and to touch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Motives thereof;
<note n="q" place="margin">Ut non modo caſus eventuſque re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio etiam, cauſaque noſcantur. 14. <hi>Ann.</hi>
                  </note> by this an
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> diſtinguiſhes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and makes himſelf conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; and nothing is more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in a Narration, than the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of what is ſecret, and of Importance in thoſe Peoples De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and Intentions, whoſe Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons it relates; and <hi>Hiſtory</hi> having nothing more commendable than this, all the little
<hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> even of the ſmalleſt Credit, have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to excell in that way. For, nothing ſtrikes more upon the Curioſity of men, than this, by which they are made to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern what is more concealed in mens
<hi>Minds;</hi> that is to ſay, the <pb n="65" facs="tcp:62282:44"/> ſecret motions which make them act, even in their ordinary Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings. It is only by going up to the Cauſe, that you will ſee the minds of thoſe you ſpeak of; that you'll diſcover the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which makes them act what they are capable of, and that you'll find the Truth by ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deeply into their Intentions. But with how many Falſhoods are <hi>Hiſtories</hi> fill'd upon this fair Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text? And, into how many Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors do unjuſt, falſe, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> daily fall, which abandon themſelves to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures; diſtribute their own Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations to the Publick, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Deſigns of thoſe whom they ſpeak of? As for Example; That
<hi>Pericles</hi> cauſed the War in <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> becauſe he lov'd <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſia:</hi> That <hi>Xerxes</hi> carry'd that dreadful Army,
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> tells us, only to eat Figs: That <hi>M. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> loſt the Empire, meerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not part with <hi>Cleopatra:</hi> That
<hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt of <hi>France,</hi> carry'd his Armies over
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62282:45"/> into <hi>Italy,</hi> only upon the account of the faire Lady named <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricea.</hi> There is nothing more tickliſh and difficult than to ſearch into mens hearts, and thence to gueſs or diſcover what they think; for an Author will tell all he knows, and all that comes into his mind, rather than fail telling the Truth. It is one of the greateſt failings in <hi>Davila,</hi> whoſe Diſcourſes are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe juſt enough; but his conjectures in the motives of the Actions he relates, do not prove very true, if we may take the Truth from their Fathers. Not but that, after all, an Action ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well clear'd to its very Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and a Secret well penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, might give a great Idea of the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi>'s Ability, and make us judge, that he ſpeaks like a man well inform'd, and looks ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well in
<hi>Hiſtory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that an Author,
<note n="r" place="margin">Haud facile animus rerum provider, ubi officiunt odium, amicitia, ira, atque miſericordia. <hi>Caeſar. apud Saluſt.</hi> in <hi>Catil.</hi>
                  </note> who pretends to gueſs, be always up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="67" facs="tcp:62282:45"/> his Guards againſt prejudice; that he hearkens neither to his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection nor his Hatred; to avoid Artifice, and thoſe Colours men are prompt to give to things, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of that ſide he is prejudic'd for; that he inſerts no falſhoods, to juſtifie his Conjectures, and to make things agree with that Air he is pleas'd to give them; that he neither diminiſh nor exagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate any thing, as <hi>Tacitus,</hi> who caſts a Poiſon every where; or as <hi>Paterculus,</hi> who ſtrows every thing with Flowers. Let him not ſhew men worſe affected than they are, as
<hi>Herodotus</hi> does, when he ſays, that the <hi>Perſians</hi> were call'd into <hi>Greece</hi> by the <hi>Spartiates,</hi> becauſe they could reſiſt the <hi>Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> no longer, nor ſuffer them, as
<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>Plutarch.</hi> de <hi>Herod.</hi> Malig.</note> 
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> reproaches him; let him not alſo cover an unjuſt dealing with a good intention, as <hi>Callias</hi> of
<hi>Syracuſe,</hi> who juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies all the Actions of <hi>Agathocles,</hi> becauſe he did him ſome good, as
<note n="t" place="margin">Excerp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Conſt. ex <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doro.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Diodorus</hi> takes notice; nor as <hi>Paulus Jovius,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:62282:46"/> 
                  <hi>de Medicis,</hi> not long ſince. There are in all
<hi>Hiſtorians</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes of that kind, becauſe they are few that have a mind ſteddy enough to reſiſt their Prejudice. But thô the motives in great men ought regularly to be better and greater than their Actions; for the motives depend upon them, but the events do not: yet it is but a ſmall miſtake, as Noble men are, to mix in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and in their Deliberations part of the pride and of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they are ſubject to: for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes it is only through ſome impertinent and ridiculous mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, that the moſt part of men are determind. There is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of Examples there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which I leave, that I may not exceed bounds upon that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. You muſt, above all things, know well the Vanity, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, the Ignorance, and the Folly of mens minds, which always conforms to their Principles, to know well the bottom of their Intentions, and ſearch his Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <pb n="69" facs="tcp:62282:46"/> which is the great Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Malice; and above all things, not to be ignorant, that the Lazineſs of moſt great men, in examining the bottom of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and the impatience they have to judge of them upon what the Conduct moſt eſſential to their Affairs depends. It is them we muſt neceſſarily know, for being, as they are, the Great Actors upon the Stage of this World, all things, for the moſt part, are rul'd by their Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies: But it does not follow, that if we have done once well in this way, by chance, we ſhould be able to do it always. There are
<hi>Hiſtorians</hi> in this Age, which have ruin'd their Reputation by too great an itch of mingling their Conjectures with all Events, and impoſing their own Conceits upon the <hi>Publick</hi> inſtead of <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> as <hi>Herrera,</hi> who ſays, that the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> did not do the beſt he could againſt the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> to manage them with Policy. There is nothing more contrary to an <pb n="70" facs="tcp:62282:47"/>
                  <hi>Hiſtorian</hi>'s mind, (who ought to be ſincere and faithful) than thoſe conjectures which are built in the Air, without any Foundation, and all Diſcourſes grounded upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conjectures, are either uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or frivolous. This is what muſt be obſerv'd in Tranſitions, in Circumſtances, and in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives wherein the chief Art of a Narration conſiſts. This is alſo what muſt be regarded in its o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts, which are the Figures, the Paſſions, the Deſcriptions, the Speeches, the Reflections, or the Sentences; the Characters of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the Digreſſions, and all that can enter in the Oeconomy of the Diſcourſe which <hi>Hiſtory</hi> ought to be made of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>XVI. Figures.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hiſtory</hi> makes uſe of Figures only to animate it ſelf<hi>:</hi> The Speaker, who has a mind to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſpeaks always by Figures, that the Springs of his Art may <pb n="71" facs="tcp:62282:47"/> play the better<hi>:</hi> but the <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> whoſe mind is only to inſtruct, ought to uſe them in another way. That very Simplicity which Truth requires in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> does not take that way of figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating, which would injure its Candor and Ingenuity.
<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> de conſer. Hiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> who is admirable every where elſe, is not here ſo much as againſt thoſe vain Ornaments of Eloquence, which are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for <hi>Hiſtory.</hi> If, ſays he, you lay on too many of them, you'll make it like <hi>Hercules,</hi> dreſt with his Miſtreſs's Cloathes; which is the greateſt of all Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies. It is yet leſs capable, continues he, of thoſe clear marks Poetry uſes, to cauſe thoſe moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in mens hearts, by moving the Paſſions. That <hi>Hiſtory</hi> which is candid and ſincere, and does not deſign to impoſe upon me, ought to leave my heart free, to judge the better of what it tells me. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, which by its Character, is an Art that impoſes, may ſteal upon my Liberty, by ſtriving to <pb n="72" facs="tcp:62282:48"/> perſuade me againſt my will. But an
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> which fixes it ſelf pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly within the Limits of Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cannot handſomely make uſe of Figures, no further than to take from the Diſcourſe its natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral coldneſs, and to render it leſs tedious. It is only by theſe means that <hi>Herodotus, Thucydides</hi> and
<hi>Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon,</hi> keep up the Reader's mind: And <hi>Saluji, Livy</hi> and
<hi>Mariana,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver uſe Figures to impoſe upon the Publick.
<hi>Tacitus</hi> is not ſo ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; he looks like a man who thinks of nothing but of dazling your Eyes: The boldneſs of his Metaphors, and of his other Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, make his Expreſſions trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome and too high.
<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.
<hi>Cic.</hi> in <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> is upon another Extream; It is a Diſcourſe naked, without Figures, unprovided of all Attire. It is not but that a figur'd Expreſſion, made on purpoſe, might pleaſe ſometimes more than proper words, becauſe it makes the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages livelier, and more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the mind, and gives ſtrength and nobleneſs to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; <pb n="73" facs="tcp:62282:48"/> and there is a boldneſs of Style, provided it be wiſe and judicious, which is admitted in places that want Life. But for Figures, to be well applied, be ſure they be modeſt and familiar, not taking the flights of Poetry, or high Eloquence; Let them not be, ſays <hi>Lucian,</hi> too bright, nor too elaborate, unleſs in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a Battel, or in a Speech, where an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> may ſpread the Sails of his Eloquence, without ſoaring too high.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>XVII. The Paſſions.</head>
               <p>The Paſſions alſo make one of the great Ornaments of the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, when they are on purpoſe, and that they are touch't judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. The Truth is, that they do not require that heat which ought to accompany the Stage<hi>:</hi> one muſt give them another Air; for they are not to be acted, but rehearſed. An <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> may make his Diſcourſe paſſionate, <pb n="74" facs="tcp:62282:49"/> but he ought not to be paſſionate himſelf. Therefore let him ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy men to the bottom, that he may lay open in his own mind the moſt private motions Paſſion is capable of raiſing there, that he may expreſs its trouble and diſorder; and that well applied, is very agreeable in a Narration. <hi>Thucydides</hi> has treated that part better than <hi>Herodotus;</hi> for he is more eloquent, and more pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, as
<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dionyſ. Halicar.</hi> Epiſt. ad
<hi>Pompei.</hi> &amp; de Virt. Serm.</note> 
                  <hi>Dionyſius Halycarnaſſaeus</hi> ſays, thô <hi>Herodotus</hi> has ſometimes more life. <hi>Hermogenes</hi> propounds an admirable Model of a tender, affectionate, and paſſionate Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the Death of <hi>Panthaea,</hi> Queen of <hi>Suſiana,</hi> which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Seventh Book of
<hi>Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon</hi>'s <hi>Cyropoedia.</hi> It is one of the fineſt places in that Author: All is ſaid in a touching Strain. <hi>Photius</hi> aſſures us, that <hi>Joſephus</hi> has a great Art in his Diſcourſe, to move the Soul by the Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<note n="z" place="margin">Affectus eos praecipue, qui commendavit.</note> 
                  <hi>Quintillian</hi> affirms, that dulciores ſunt, nemo Hiſtoricorum <hi>Livio</hi> magis <hi>Fab.</hi> l. 10. c. 1.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62282:49"/> 
                  <hi>Livy,</hi> of all <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> has moſt ſignaliz'd himſelf by thoſe tender and delicate ways, whereby he has entertain'd the ſweeteſt moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Soul: <hi>Affectus eos prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipue, qui dulciores ſunt, nemo Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricorum</hi> Livio <hi>magis commendavit.</hi> Fabius, <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 1. The Rape of the
<hi>Sabins,</hi> thoſe tender moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they ſhew'd at that time to take the Arms out of the hands of the <hi>Romans,</hi> their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and of the
<hi>Sabins,</hi> their Fathers; the Death of <hi>Lucretia;</hi> Her Body expoſed to Publick View, to move the People to rebell againſt the
<hi>Tarquins; Vet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turia</hi> at her Son <hi>Cariolanus</hi>'s Feet, to appeaſe his Fury, when he came to beſiege <hi>Rome; Virginia</hi> ſtabb'd by her Father; the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation of <hi>Rome,</hi> after the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel of
<hi>Cannae;</hi> and a thouſand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch things, touch't in his
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> by the moſt tender Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions imaginable, are fine Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples thereof. And it is in that <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> you ought to ſtudy the way of treating Paſſions as they <pb n="76" facs="tcp:62282:50"/> ought to be in
<hi>Hiſtory;</hi> for he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimates himſelf only in the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where heat is requiſite. <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> does not mind how to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage his heat; he is always paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate; and even thoſe Colours he uſes, are always too ſtrong: and becauſe he is ſtill too full in ſome things, and that he does not Copy after Nature, he does not move ſo much. I ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the other <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> the greateſt number of whom have not underſtood the Paſſions, nor the way they ought to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in. It is a particular kind of <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> which requires a great Senſe, and a very exact knowledge of Morality. But, if we intend to pleaſe, let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of thoſe Dry Narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are void of the moving ſtroaks which Nature requires.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:62282:50"/>
               <head>XVIII. The Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</head>
               <p>That Affectation which appears in moſt <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> in making De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, has, in a manner, run down its uſe amongſt judicious people. Nothing indeed is more childiſh, than a Deſcription too much poliſh'd in a ſerious <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.</hi> Young Authors run head-long into it, without diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: You cannot be too circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in the uſe thereof. The Principle which is obſervable in it, is, That you muſt uſe it no more than is neceſſary to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate thoſe things, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge whereof is eſſential to what you write. Such is the Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Capraea, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Annal. Tacit.</hi> For it denotes the Reaſon <hi>Tyberius</hi> had to retire thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toward the latter end of his life, which renders it neceſſary; and being ſhort, eloquent, and poliſh'd, without any Superflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, one may ſay, that it is as it <pb n="78" facs="tcp:62282:51"/> ought to be. The Deſcription
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sal.</hi> in Bello
<hi>Jugurt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Saluſt</hi> made of the place where
<hi>Jugurtha</hi> was defeated by <hi>Metellus,</hi> ſerves to make one know the Fight better. You may ſee there the Vertue of the <hi>Roman,</hi> as well as the Experience of the <hi>Numidian</hi> King, by the advantage he had taken in poſſeſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the Hills: and all the recital of the Battel, is better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, by that draught of the place which the
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> lays be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Eyes, as well as the Picture of that place, where <hi>Hannibal</hi> fought <hi>Minucius,</hi> Book 22. <hi>Annal. Livii,</hi> which is a place well touch'd. Deſcriptions might again be allow'd in a great <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi> to make the Narration more pleaſing, provided they be fitted well to the purpoſe, and free from that ſuperfluity which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly accompanies them, when given by young <hi>Hiſtorians.</hi> The deſire they have to ſhew their Parts that way, makes them fall in a pittiful childiſhneſs. Nay,
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> de Hiſt. conſer.</note> 
                  <hi>Lucian</hi> finds fault with the <pb n="79" facs="tcp:62282:51"/> too long Deſcription which <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidides</hi> makes of the Plague of
<hi>Athens,</hi> in the Second Book of his Hiſtory; and he is, perhaps, in the right: for that Author, thô wiſe, runs into a Narration of that Diſeaſe too particular: But that Critick has more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, when he complains of that impertinent <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> of his Time, who took ſo much delight in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king great Deſcriptions of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, of Cities, of Battels, which, he ſays, out-do in Coldneſs, all the Snows, and all the Ice of the <hi>North.</hi> And indeed, nothing is colder than a deſcription which is too much ſtudied. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines of War us'd by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> are deſcrib'd in his Commentaries, with a way of Circumſtances too great for ſo mecanick a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as that is. That <hi>Commander,</hi> whoſe Reputation in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of War, is eſtabliſh'd, ſeems to have a deſire to be thought alſo a good <hi>Engineer;</hi> it looks too much affected for a man ſo judicious. The Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <pb n="80" facs="tcp:62282:52"/> of <hi>Africa,</hi> in the War of <hi>Jugurtha</hi> in <hi>Saluſt,</hi> is too full of Circumſtances. There was no need of ſo many to mark the Limits of the Kingdoms of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therbal</hi> and <hi>Jugurtha,</hi> which were then in diſpute: What need was there to deſcribe all that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and to make a diſtinction of the Manners of the People, with ſo much particularity? De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions muſt then be uſeful, exact, ſhort, elegant, never ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, having no harſhneſs in them, nor a vain deſire of making your Wit appear more than your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that your Deſcriptions may look well, as thoſe of <hi>Livy</hi> do: 'twere fit you ſhould make him your Pattern.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>XIX. Speeches.</head>
               <p>I find the Maſters Opinions very much divided in that Point.
<hi>Herodotus, Thucydides,</hi> and <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon,</hi> have ſignaliz'd themſelves chiefly by their Speeches: <hi>Thucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dides</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:62282:52"/> did better than any of them; the Speeches of the chiefeſt Actors in his <hi>Hiſtory, Pericles, Nicias, Alcibiades, Archidamus,</hi> and of all the Nations that ſpeak by Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are excellent Leſſons for Speakers of all Ages; and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> formed himſelf chiefly in that School. <hi>Polybius</hi> uſes more Formalities<hi>:</hi> he doth not let <hi>Scipio</hi> ſpeak ſo much, thô he has reaſon to do it, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been his Companion in War;
<note n="c" place="margin">In Sermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus effingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis
<hi>Herodotus, Thucydides, Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon, Saluſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> nimii vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur: &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa eſt cur <hi>Caeſar</hi> Commentarios ſcripſit, ut id omitteret, in quo alii labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. <hi>Biſciol.</hi> l. 7. hor. ſubceſſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> is ſtill more ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; for he makes hardly any Speeches at all, pretending they are againſt the Truth of
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and taking rather the part of writing bare Memories, that he may ſeem plainer in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. <hi>Dionyſius Halycarnaſſaeus</hi> cauſes <hi>Brutus</hi> to make a long Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation upon the Death of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretia,</hi> that ſo he might excite the People to Revenge; and that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which he makes <hi>Valerius</hi> to ſpeak upon the fitteſt form of Government in a State, Book 7. of his <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> is very tedious. <pb n="82" facs="tcp:62282:53"/> 
                  <hi>Joſephus, Appian, Dio Caſſius,</hi> and <hi>Procopius,</hi> are great Diſcourſers, as well as
<hi>Thucydides</hi> and <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon,</hi> which took that Idea of ſpeaking out of <hi>Homer:</hi> And in truth, if we examine the grounds of thoſe Diſcourſes, and, above all, of thoſe that are made by Captains, to encourage the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to fight, we ſhall find but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle likelihood in them.
<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Trogus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendit in
<hi>Livio</hi> &amp; <hi>Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtio,</hi> quod Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciones &amp; Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones operi ſuo inſerendo, hiſtoriae mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum exceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint. <hi>Juſt.</hi> l. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> reproaches <hi>Saluſt</hi> and <hi>Livy,</hi> with a great deal of reaſon, for the immoderate exceſs of Speeches in their
<hi>Hiſtories:</hi> And indeed all thoſe Diſcourſes they attribute to great men, have but a falſe look: for out of what Memoires could they have taken them? Beſides, a Warrier don't ſpeak like one that makes it his buſineſs to ſpeak in publick.
<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Livius, Thucydides</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſerunt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciones, quae nunquam abiis, quibus ſunt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributae cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae fuerunt. <hi>Scal.</hi> Poet. l. 1.</note> So when
<hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> in <hi>Thucydides,</hi> made an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in praiſe of his Soldiers that had been defeated and kill'd by the <hi>Boeotians:</hi> His Speech is feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as well as that which <hi>Cati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line,</hi> in
<hi>Saluſt,</hi> makes to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators,</hi> which, in all probability, <pb n="83" facs="tcp:62282:53"/> was ſecret, and not much ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This is partly what
<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ben.</hi> l. 2. de Hiſt.</note>
                  <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> ſays, to improve that miſtake. <hi>Thucydides,</hi> who was judicious, took care of that in his laſt Books, where he makes fewer Speeches than in the firſt. But it is a Natural Leſſon; for we never write an
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> but we bring in thoſe that have a ſhare in it, to make them ſpeak; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing gives more vigour to a Narration, which is apt to grow cold by a Diſcourſe too much poliſhed. There is then a
<hi>medium</hi> to be taken: A ſmall Diſcourſe made on purpoſe in an
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> by one that bears a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter fit to make it, being alſo well ſuited to the Perſon and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject under hand, may pleaſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put in its due place. But thoſe formal Speeches at the Head of an Army ready to engage, and thoſe Deliberations of a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious prolixity, which are made upon thoſe buſineſſes that are ſpoken of, are almoſt out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion in good <hi>Hiſtories:</hi> And the <pb n="84" facs="tcp:62282:54"/> wiſeſt chuſe to make their <hi>Heroe</hi> ſpeak things in few words, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out engaging themſelves to ſay ſet Speeches; as <hi>Livy,</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> has done by the Embaſſadors which <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus</hi> ſent to his Neighbours. The moſt part of <hi>Saluſt</hi>'s Speeches are very fine, but never to the purpoſe; for nothing is finer than
<hi>Marius</hi>'s Speech: It is the beſt Moral Lecture in the World upon Nobility; all is reaſonable in it; and Antiquity has few of that Strength, to perſuade People to embrace Vertue; but it is ſet in a wrong place; and the way that he makes <hi>Cato</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> give their Opinion in the
<hi>Senate,</hi> how great ſoever it be, is not made proportionable to the reſt of his <hi>Hiſtory.</hi> Of that number is the long Diſcourſe
<hi>Dio</hi> makes in the 56<hi>th</hi> Book of his <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> in praiſe of Marriage, and of a Batchelor's Life. But on the contrary, there is nothing firmer than <hi>Tyberius</hi>'s Speech upon the Reformation of
<hi>Luxury, Tacit. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Annal.</hi> No <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:62282:54"/> ever made a Prince ſpeak with more Dignity. The Speeches of <hi>Agrippa</hi> and of <hi>Moecenas</hi> to <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus,</hi> wherein the one adviſes him to quit the Empire, and the other to keep it, are extream fine in <hi>Dio Caſſius;</hi> but they are ſo long, that they take up all the 52<hi>d</hi> Book. In fine, to finiſh this Article, I am for
<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Thucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dide</hi> Orationes quas interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit laudare ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leo: ſed imitari neque poſſim ſi velim, neque velim ſi poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim. <hi>Cic.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar. Orat.</note>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi>'s Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, who ſpeaking of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of
<hi>Thucidides,</hi> ſays wiſely, <hi>I find them very fine, and I could not do ſo well if I would, nor would I do it if I could;</hi> which is all that can be well ſaid upon that Subject; For, in fine, Speakers are always ſubject to be tedious<hi>:</hi> And <hi>Boccalinus</hi> is very pleaſant, who condemns an Old Man to the Pennance of reading one of <hi>Guichardin</hi>'s Speeches, becauſe he had read a <hi>Madrigall,</hi> with his Spectacles, upon
<hi>Mount Parnaſſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:62282:55"/>
               <head>XX. The Characters of Perſons.</head>
               <p>Pictures are a great Embel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhment in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> when well drawn; but <hi>Romances</hi> have ſpoil'd that way; for we make too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and thoſe ſuch as do not well reſemble: We loſe time in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing, after our own Fancy, the Air of the Perſon: but this is not the thing
<note n="h" place="margin">Explicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur hominum ipſorum non ſolum res ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtae, ſed vita ac natura. <hi>Cic.</hi> l. 2. de Orat.</note>
                  <hi>:</hi> For what does it ſignifie to me to know whether
<hi>Hannibal</hi> had good Teeth, provided that his <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ſhew me the greatneſs of his Genius; that he ſhew me a bold and an active Spirit, vaſt Thoughts, a ſtout Heart, and all that anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by an extream Ambition, and ſupported too by a ſtrong Conſtitution, as
<note n="i" place="margin">Libr. 21. Annal.</note> 
                  <hi>Livy</hi> has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd it? So <hi>Saluſt</hi> gives me a great Opinion of
<hi>Catiline,</hi> by the Picture he makes of him at the beginning of his
<hi>Hiſtory:</hi> And when I ſee that deſperate Soldier raiſe Armies in his Cloſet, go up <pb n="87" facs="tcp:62282:55"/> to the <hi>Senate</hi> with a Silence that ſhews his Reſolution to affront the Conſul; to hear, unconcern'd, his Invectives; to put <hi>Rome</hi> in Allarm, to make <hi>Italy</hi> tremble; to dare at laſt what no Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ever durſt; I am not ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd, after the Deſcription the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> has made me of him: I ſee a Man of Reſolution, who ſtirs all things, without being ſeen, becauſe he had taken well his meaſure. <hi>Pompey</hi> is far off with the beſt Troops of the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> tied by a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, thô neceſſary War; <hi>Rome</hi> full of Factious People, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces full of Malecontents<hi>:</hi> there's a general Diſorder in the
<hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> through a Deluge of Vice which overwhelm'd it; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing favours <hi>Catiline</hi>'s Deſign, in the Conjuncture he found of putting it in execution. So one may gueſs what might happen of the War of
<hi>Atherbal</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurtha,</hi> after <hi>Saluſt</hi>'s Deſcription of the Genius's of both; that I know to the bottom <hi>Sylla</hi> and <pb n="88" facs="tcp:62282:56"/> 
                  <hi>Marius,</hi> according to the Idea he has given me of them, and that I take pleaſure to ſee, iſſuing from their Spring which that <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> has diſcover'd unto me, the Sequel of
<hi>Jugurtha</hi>'s great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, who gave ſo great diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance to the
<hi>Romans,</hi> after the Image he has drawn of that Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. It is in that manner that the Ancients have mix'd in their <hi>Hiſtories</hi> thoſe kind of Pictures of the Perſons they deſign'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, to diſtinguiſh them from others; which is of great Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a Piece, when done op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunely: For after a Character is well eſtabliſh'd by thoſe Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Features, which make a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of it, all goes on a great deal better; all things are better underſtood in the Narration: But it is a Maſter-piece, to hit that Reſemblance, which conſiſts only in ſingular and impercepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Features, which alone expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Nature, and which one hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meets with, unleſs he ſearches the hearts, and unwraps all their <pb n="89" facs="tcp:62282:56"/> folds, that he may well know what is hidden. But what ſtrength of Spirit, and what acuteneſs is requiſite for that purpoſe? Theſe things that follow are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in it: Firſt, the Picture ought to be real; and this was <hi>Xenophon</hi>'s miſcarriage in the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture he made of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he gave nothing but the Idea of an
<hi>Heroe.</hi> Secondly, it ought to reſemble: in that <hi>Tacitus</hi> has not been exact enough, minding to follow rather his Genius, than to imitate Nature; ſeeking more to make a good Picture, than to give the reſemblance, provided that his Pictures pleaſe; as that of <hi>Sejanus, lib.</hi> 4.
<hi>Annal.</hi> He cares but little whether they reſemble or not; for he makes him a great deal worſe than he is, if we may believe
<hi>Paterculus,</hi> who praiſes him much. Thirdly, an Author ought to make only the Pictures of Perſons of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence<hi>:</hi> There
<hi>Saluſt</hi> miſtook in the Repreſentation of <hi>Sempronia,</hi> who makes but an indifferent Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure <pb n="90" facs="tcp:62282:57"/> in <hi>Catiline</hi>'s Conſpiracy. But althô too much time ought not to be ſpent in painting the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Parts of the Perſon, yet he may do it in ſome caſes, when that may ſerve to make the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of thoſe you ſpeak of better underſtood. And indeed there are ſeveral ways of painting<hi>:</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lucretiam</hi> nocte ſera non in convivio luxuque ſed deditam lanae inter Ancillas ſedentem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniunt,
<hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Annal.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> ſpeaking of
<hi>Lucretia,</hi> ſo fair to her Husband's Eyes, without mentioning any thing of her Face, paints only her Virtue, and gives in one word, the greateſt Idea that can be given of an honeſt Woman. <hi>Tacitus</hi> paints
<hi>Tyberius</hi> only by his Actions; that way he makes him to be known<hi>:</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Oppreſſit in Tricliniis Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſytos ſuos violis &amp; flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſicut ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam aliqui efflaverint,
<hi>Lampr.</hi> in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liog.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Lampridius</hi> makes a right Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the Emperour <hi>Heliogaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> ſaying, that he ſtifl'd his <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſites</hi> in heaps of Flowers, after he had drown'd them with Wine: <hi>Procopius</hi> paints the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Theodora</hi> by her Gallantries: A drinking bout is ſufficient to the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> that writes <hi>Venceſlaus</hi>'s Life, to draw the Picture of that Emperour; who caus'd, ſays he, <pb n="91" facs="tcp:62282:57"/> his Cook to be put upon the Spit, and roaſted, becauſe he had ill roaſted a Pig which that Prince had a mind to eat. But the beſt way of painting, is to diſcover the ſecret motions of the heart, which makes the Perſon better known. It is from thence only that you ought to take thoſe Features which make a diſtinction, that you may give a Character rais'd from its own ground. All the reſt ought to be little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of in a ſerious <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> which can endure nothing but what is judicious. I ſhould not like alſo thoſe Pictures which are copied, and taken here and there, as in <hi>Mariana;</hi> thoſe he took out of <hi>Tacitus:</hi> Nor like that of <hi>Walſtein,</hi> in
<note n="m" place="margin">A <hi>French</hi> Author, who wrote part of <hi>Walſtein</hi>'s Conſpiracy.</note> 
                  <hi>Sarraſin,</hi> which is made up, for the moſt part, of the fineſt Pictures in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity. You ought not to loſe time in Copies, when you draw after the Life, and when you think of making an Original. After all is done, <hi>Hiſtory</hi> is the faithfulleſt Picture of thoſe you <pb n="92" facs="tcp:62282:58"/> ſpeak of; nothing ſhewing their Character better than the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of their Actions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>XXI. The Reflections and Sentences.</head>
               <p>There is much to be ſaid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Article, which makes all the delight of <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> when deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately done: but there are many miſtakes to be avoided in this Point, where you can never uſe too much Simplicity. <hi>Xenophon, Polybius,</hi> and <hi>Tacitus,</hi> are full of Reflections; <hi>Thucydides, Saluſt,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> are more reſerv'd. What Party muſt an Author chuſe amongſt ſo great Examples of ſo different a Conduct, and in ſo important a matter. And, in truth, the Beauty which <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory</hi> hopes for from that kind of Ornament, requires to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd with exact judgment: For, in fine, a man quits the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of an <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> who ought to tell naturally, what he has to ſay, without mingling, <hi>mal à pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos,</hi> 
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:62282:58"/> his own Conceits with it, when he moralizes upon all ſorts of things, turning, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, the Adventures which offer themſelves, great and ſmall, into curious and Political Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Nothing alſo is more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of adulterating Truth, or, at leaſt, of perplexing it, than thoſe fine thoughts, which ſome Authors ſhuffle in out of their own brains, and which a Reader often has not Wit enough to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh from the ground of
<hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.</hi> It is then Wiſdom in an Author to have no ſrivolous Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of his own, to play the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher's part indifferently upon every thing that preſents it ſelf before him; as <hi>Ammianus Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus,</hi> who acts too much like a Philoſopher, by an Affectation of appearing Learned, which is but little underſtood. <hi>Livy</hi> goes on his way, ſtopping at nothing; he ſays what he knows of the things he ſpeaks of, and leaves the Reader at liberty to make Reflections, without preventing <pb n="94" facs="tcp:62282:59"/> him with his own: and when he does it, it is only with few words, but Noble and Great;
<note n="n" place="margin">Deos eſſe non negligere humana, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbiae &amp; cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitati, &amp; ſi ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, non leves poenas venire,
<hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Annal.</hi>
                  </note> as what he ſays of the Crime and Puniſhment of <hi>Appius,</hi> who had ſtollen away <hi>Virginia.</hi> It is a great Gift in an Author, to know how to furniſh his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with Matters to apply their Minds to, to draw Conſequences, and to give what Air he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the things related. All Readers will have their liberty to think what they pleaſe upon what is preſented to them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being pre-engag'd; and the uſe of that liberty is one of the greateſt delights he takes in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Let us then retrench thoſe deep and abſtracted Reflections, if we mean to pleaſe; not labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after much Spruceneſs in what we write: Let us be more natural and candid; Let us ſay the Truth, without commenting upon it, if our Wit be ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to bear it; Let us, above all things, forbear to moralize upon Fortune, and her Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancies,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:62282:59"/> a thing ſo common in Books; Let us not affect thoſe Sententious Expreſſions, which have too much Gayity and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament; Let us renounce thoſe Witticiſms, and falſe Sentiments, which Authors of a ſmall Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us jingle with. If we mix in our Diſcourſe ſome Reflections, let them be as natural as may be, and ſuch as ariſe from the Subject it ſelf; let them never be too fine, nor too elaborate; let them be more ſolid, thô leſs ornamental; let them look more like the Arguments of a wiſe <hi>Politician,</hi> than the Affectation of an Orator;
<note n="o" place="margin">Curandum ne ſententiaee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineant extra corpus oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis expreſſae, <hi>Petr.</hi>
                  </note> Let him be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too frequent, nor too looſe, but woven, as one may ſay, in the Body of your Work: In fine, let them never have that lofty look of Reflections, which give an ill Opinion of him that makes them. It is in that that <hi>Tacitus, Machiavel, Paulus Jovius, Davila,</hi> and moſt part of the
<hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> are exceſſive. But let none adventure to make <pb n="96" facs="tcp:62282:60"/> thoſe curious Reflections of
<hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> and <hi>Morality,</hi> unleſs he knows the Man entirely, the Illuſions of his Spirit, and the Weakneſs of his Mind. It is only by that knowledge that good <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> are diſtinguiſh'd from thoſe of a middle Rank, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Lives. <hi>Saluſt,</hi> thô unaffected, preaches too much againſt the Corruptions and Ill Manners of his own Time; he is always an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with his Countrey, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways diſſatisfied with the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: he gives too bad an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the
<hi>Commonwealth,</hi> through his Invectives, and his Reflections upon the Luxury of <hi>Rome.</hi> In truth, thô there is nothing falſe in what he ſays, yet he runs out of his firſt thoughts. So <hi>Davila</hi> would make fewer Speeches, did he but remember that he is an <hi>Hiſtorian.</hi> It is neceſſary to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Morality well, to make juſt Reflections; For true Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is the ground of good Policy. Therefore <hi>Tacitus</hi>'s Policy is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten falſe, becauſe his Morality is <pb n="97" facs="tcp:62282:60"/> not true<hi>:</hi> either he makes Men appear too much corrupted, or he is not candid enough him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: There is nothing natural commonly in his Reflections, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing is innocent in them; he envenoms, and gives an ill turn to every thing: He has by that means ſpoil'd many People, who imitate him in that Article, not being able to do it in any other. And this muſt be obſerv'd upon the uſe of Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in <hi>Hiſtory.</hi> A Sentence may be put in the Mouth of a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter fit to ſpeak Sentences: <hi>Mariana,</hi> as well as <hi>Strada,</hi> do not ſeem to manage that well. People alſo have no great affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for thoſe ſtiff men which never yield to any thing, and who, to make what they ſay ſeem more important, multiply Sentences upon Sentences, Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon Reflections, and by a ridiculous Gravity, will ſeem <hi>Cato</hi>'s in ſmall trifles. The too great ſubtilty in thoſe refinings of Conjecture, is apt to degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:62282:61"/> in a falſe delicacy; and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections are good only when they leaſt appear to be ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>XXII. Digreſſions.</head>
               <p>Digreſſions have alſo their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeableneſs, when they are made in fit times, and that they have nothing too wide, nor too looſe, becauſe it gives to a Narration a Variety ſo neceſſary to make it agreeable; but they ought to be wiſely mixed. An Author is apt to err when he goes from his Subject; for one whoſe head is not ſtrong enough changes eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and to quit your matter without precaution, to ſeek Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, and carry your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der abroad, does not belong ſo much to an
<hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> as to a Writer of Adventures, who ſticks upon every thing he finds to ſtuff up his Relation. He takes Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, he fights Battels, he finds Adventures every where; as <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus,</hi> who continually goes from <pb n="99" facs="tcp:62282:61"/> his Text, by his too frequent, and often forc'd Digreſſions; thô he took Example by <hi>Homer,</hi> who is indeed a great Maſter; for thô he ſoars often, he goes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs ſtrait enough to his Mark, without loſing time in things out of ſeaſon.
<hi>Thucydides</hi> has a better Order than <hi>Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus;</hi> he confines himſelf ſtrictly to his Subject<hi>:</hi> The Conſpiracy of
<hi>Harmodius</hi> and <hi>Ariſtogyton,</hi> in the Sixth Book, is one of thoſe Narrations wherein he has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell'd moſt. <hi>Xenophon</hi> endeavours to imitate him: If he forgets himſelf ſometimes, as he has done,
<hi>lib.</hi> 5. of the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> in the Adventure concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Panthaea,</hi> yet that Adventure has a natural Relation to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of his Hiſtory; <hi>Panthaea</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been taken by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> in the Overthrow of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> and <hi>Abradatus,</hi> her Husband, by that means coming to <hi>Cyrus</hi>'s ſide, and becoming one of the chiefeſt of his Army. The plain Truth is, I would not be reſponſible for <pb n="94" facs="tcp:62282:62"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:62282:62"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:62282:63"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:62282:63"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:62282:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:62282:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:62282:65"/> the other Digreſſions of that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, which are not quite ſo well coupled to his Subject in his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Works.
<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Polybius</hi> &amp;
<hi>Saluſtius</hi> ita peccarunt, ut nullam un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam veniam impetrarint dum digredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ex <hi>Sebaſt. Macr.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Polybius</hi> has fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Digreſſions upon Policy, knowledge of Arms, and upon the Laws of <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> which do not appear very neceſſary: <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſt</hi> ſometimes commits the ſame Fault, wherein a Modern Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick blames them both. <hi>Photius</hi> praiſes much the Digreſſion of <hi>Dionyſius Halycarnaſſaeus, lib.</hi> 7. to deſcribe the Conſequence of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtodemus</hi>'s Tyranny. The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion about the Phoenix, <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Annal. Tacit.</hi> upon the news which came to <hi>Rome,</hi> of a Phoenix which had appear'd in
<hi>Egypt,</hi> under the Reign of <hi>Tyberius,</hi> is according to the Rules of a juſt Digreſſion: The Queſtion is examin'd by the ſeveral Opinions of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſts upon that Bird; his Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, his Shape, all is deſcrib'd there in few words. A Digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that kind ſet in a due place, is of great Ornament to a Narration, and that helps to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:62282:65"/> ſpur the Curioſity of a Reader, and to rouze his Spirits. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing alſo in <hi>Mariana</hi>'s Hiſtory contributes ſo much to that Air of greatneſs which it has, as the Art which he has of bringing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, by way of Digreſſion, all that has happen'd conſiderable in the World, of admirable inefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous Ages, of remarkables in <hi>Greece,</hi> in
<hi>Sicily,</hi> in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire; a pretty particular Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi> which is no where elſe better than it is there; the Sieges of <hi>Saguntus</hi> and <hi>Numancia,</hi> the Paſſage of <hi>Hannibal</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>Series</hi> of Emperours, the Birth of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel, the Conqueſts of the <hi>Arabians,</hi> and many other things which look great. He has a Genius which is altogether for great matters, which hangs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſome way or other to the <hi>Spaniſh Hiſtory.</hi> No
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ever honour'd his Countrey ſo much by any Work; for he has given his Countrey the Honour of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <pb n="102" facs="tcp:62282:66"/> great thing that was ever done in the World. But as there are but few Spirits ſtrong enough to follow the Stream of an <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi> without taking breath, and tying themſelves up to their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, without going out of it; ſo there are few <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> but will ſometimes forget themſelves, by doing the contrary in their Digreſſions. I will not take the pains to mark them; they every where occur; nothing being ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer than that exact ſenſe, which knows how to apply it ſelf to its Subject: I ſhall only ſay, that
<note n="q" place="margin">Nihil mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus quaeritum à principio hujus operis, quam ut plus juſto abrerum ordine decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narem varieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibuſque di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguendo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera, legenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus veluti di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verticula quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerem, <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>Annal.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Livy</hi> has ſhunn'd nothing with more care than thoſe by-ways which led him from his matter, as himſelf declares it, nothing being leſs judicious. But in our
<hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> the ſame ridiculous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour may ſtill be found, which
<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> de Conſer. Hiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Lucian</hi> met with in his time, in them that wrote the
<hi>Parthian</hi> War, who mix'd in their Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations the fooliſheſt things in the World, to render them more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting, running from Countrey
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:62282:66"/> to Countrey, from Age to Age, from one Adventure to another, without any diſtinction. You muſt then lay it down as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and indiſpenſable Rule, That Digreſſions ought to be connect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed always, by ſomewhat or other, to the Principal Subject in hand, as
<note n="s" place="margin">Statuit non attingere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna, niſi qua Romanis co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerent rebus, <hi>Luc.</hi> l. 39. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi>
                  </note> that Judicious <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> we ſpoke of juſt now has always done; And you ought to examine well, whether in the bottom they have no natural antipathy; for if they have, they are not fit to be us'd; for nothing is more eſſential to the Digreſſion, than the Affinity it ought to have with the Subject<hi>:</hi> The great Secret is, to know ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly how far it ought to go; for it has its Natural Limits, which are not to be paſſed. That which renders the Proportion dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, is, that the Extent of them ought not always to be the ſame; for it muſt be great or ſmall, more or leſs, according to the Relation it has to the chief part of <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> and the making a right Judgment here, is the <pb n="104" facs="tcp:62282:67"/> Rock upon which all
<hi>Hiſtorians</hi> daſh; for there are few which in their Digreſſions exceed not due bounds, it being the greateſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty to keep them exactly, and to rule themſelves. In that there is a great deal to be ſaid againſt <hi>Mariana,</hi> who in the beginning of his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> has taken many ways to arrive at his Point: He has need of an <hi>Apology</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that, which I do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to juſtifie him in. The only Model a Writer may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to himſelf in this, is
<note n="t" place="margin">Ut quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere libeat qui eventus
<hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> Rebus, ſi cum <hi>Alexandro</hi> foret bellatum, futurus fuerit, <hi>Annal. l.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> who would not have left the <hi>Roman Hiſtory</hi> to tell his Mind up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Succeſs of
<hi>Alexander</hi>'s Arms, had he come into <hi>Italy,</hi> without great precautions, and ſatisfying the Reader's mind with ample Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes: The Diſcourſe he makes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is very curious, and not at all out of ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:62282:67"/>
               <head>XXIII. Eloquence fit in Hiſtory.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hiſtory</hi> ought to be Eloquent, and not tedious: In that only its Art conſiſts; that is its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Effect. But there is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Effect, known but by few people, to ſay nothing, thô true, but what has the Air of Truth, to gain Credit in the moſt difficult things to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Eloquence, which knows how to give to things the Air which may render them accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ought to be employ'd about it. And the ſetting of things in that admirable Order, which makes them probable, is its chiefeſt work; The Matter is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> in
<hi>Memoires,</hi> which People furniſh him with; but it is his buſineſs to lay them together, and to do it well: He muſt not think ſo much what he ſays, as to the manner of ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; for in this, as in all other parts of Eloquence, the Method <pb n="106" facs="tcp:62282:68"/> is all; That is properly the uſe the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ought to make of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, which alone ſets every thing in its place. It is the great Artifice of <hi>Thucydides,</hi> ſays
<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Thucydides</hi> omnes dicendi artificio vincit, <hi>Cic.</hi> l. 2. de Orat.</note> 
                  <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero,</hi> which has ſurpaſs'd all the other <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> by his Eloquence.
<note n="w" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tito Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio</hi> mirae fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundiae viro, <hi>Fab.</hi> l. 8. c. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Quintillian</hi> ſpeaks of that of
<hi>Livy</hi> with admiration. It is only by that admirable Quality that thoſe Two Great Men have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd themſelves ſo much from the Commonalty of other <hi>Hiſtorians;</hi> for it is Eloquence which gives a man the way of explaining himſelf. He perſuades beſt, who explains himſelf in the eaſieſt manner; it is perſuaſion only which gives to things that colour of Truth, which they have by no other way but by that turn which is given them, and by the light they are ſet in. So nothing is more eloquent than the Picture <hi>Saluſt</hi> makes of the Condition which
<hi>Rome</hi> was in, when <hi>Catiline</hi> took up the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of making himſelf Maſter of it: And when that admirable <pb n="107" facs="tcp:62282:68"/> Author repreſents the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> corrupted through Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Avarice, weakned under the weight of its own greatneſs; they are the fineſt Expreſſions which can be found in <hi>Hiſtory:</hi> It is in thoſe Images your Art muſt ſhew it ſelf, if you have any; and the
<hi>Hiſtorians</hi> of the firſt Rate are full of them. It is that Eloquence which ought to be mix'd with <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate it with its flame and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; for without it all is but languiſhing: and thoſe ſeveral turns one ought to embelliſh a Narration with, to make it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable; all the Art of Tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, thoſe ſo tender and paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate motions which go to the heart, that Connexion of the moſt Memorable Actions; that ordering of Circumſtances, and thoſe Embelliſhments which raiſe the Admiration, are nothing but the Effects of that ſingular Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence which is proper to <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi> which ought ſometimes to raiſe it ſelf, and ſoar aloft, when <pb n="108" facs="tcp:62282:69"/> occaſion requires it. But it is the Effect of an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi>'s Judgment, to diſtinguiſh thoſe places. A kind of Eloquence did rule over the <hi>Greeks</hi> and the <hi>Romans</hi> too, in the Speeches of thoſe which were to ſpeak, which was only meer Oſtentation, ſhewing the Wit of the <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> rather than the Truth of <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> and in that the Authors thought rather to amuſe the people, than to inſtruct them. That Eloquence is out of faſhion among the wiſe Moderns, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it had an affected way; and thoſe who have any Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, love only what is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. The Prefaces of
<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Saluſtius</hi> in bello
<hi>Jugur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thino</hi> &amp; <hi>Catili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nario</hi> nihil ad Hiſtoriam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentibus principiis uſus eſt, <hi>Fab.</hi> l. 10. c. 8.</note>
                  <hi>Saluſt,</hi> which are great Diſcourſes, full of Senſe, and very Eloquent, ſeem to me of that kind; They are common places, without any reference to his <hi>Hiſtory.</hi> That Author, perhaps, had ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, which he made uſe of in times of need; as
<note n="y" place="margin">Habeo Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumen proemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum, ex eo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligere ſoleo cum aliquod <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> inſtitui, ad <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum</hi> l. 16. <hi>ep</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Tully</hi> did, according to his own Confeſſion. I have always, ſays he, a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of Prefaces ready againſt I <pb n="109" facs="tcp:62282:69"/> have need of 'em. I would not have ſuſpected him of ſo much precaution, had not he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf bragg'd of it. That may be good for an Orator that ſpeaks always publickly, and has not always leiſure to prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; but it is not to be endur'd in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> where the Author is Maſter both of himſelf and his Time<hi>:</hi> For, to conclude, all thoſe Diſcourſes, thô never ſo fine of themſelves, ceaſe to be ſo, as ſoon as they are out of their places, and as ſoon as any Affectation appears: And this is what may be ſaid upon the Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of <hi>Hiſtory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>XXIV. The other Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which one may apply in Hiſtory.</head>
               <p>There may alſo be other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments fit to be put in
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> to make it more pleaſant, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when it is dull, and when it is too plain, by over-long Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, which are too much like one another<hi>:</hi> but, of thoſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, <pb n="110" facs="tcp:62282:70"/> the moſt apparent are not always the moſt eſſential: <hi>All is not Gold that glitters.</hi> A Mind that is bridled up does not take delight in too much finery; and that ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage a Learned Man to manage thoſe Ornaments without Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality, and accommodate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to mens Capacity, which too great a brightneſs dazles; beſides that thoſe Ornaments crowded one upon another, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe more than they pleaſe. There are hidden ones, which give greater ſatisfaction to curious people; and thô they eſcape o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers notice, they do not eſcape theirs; you may every moment diſcover new Charms which up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them, and which are la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, more than thoſe which give but a glaunce, and die. Thoſe kind of Ornaments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſometimes of eloquent or wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty turns, which in a mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r are ſurpriſing, and caſt an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look'd for Effect on the places they are put in; whereof here <pb n="111" facs="tcp:62282:70"/> are ſome Examples: <hi>Porſenna,</hi> King of <hi>Cluſium,</hi> beſieges <hi>Rome: C. Mutius,</hi> mov'd with the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger he ſees his Countrey in by ſo cloſe a Siege, goes into <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenna</hi>'s Camp, kills his Secretary cloſe by him, thinking to have kill'd him: The Murtherer is ſeis'd; they order a Pan of fire to be brought, to force him to declare his Aſſociates by the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the fire. That Young Man, full of Courage, in cold Blood, puts his hand in the fire, and without any alteration in his Countenance, let it be quite burnt upon the hot Embers; ſpeaking in this manner to the King<hi>:</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Sentias quam vile cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ſit iis, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magnam glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am vident. <hi>Tit. Liv.</hi> l. 2. <hi>Annal.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>See</hi> how <hi>thoſe that are poſſeſt with true Glory, deſpiſe their own Carcaſs.</hi> That ſpoken with a firm Countenance, alters the face of things; the Murtherer, thô abominable and odious, caſts an admiration on the Spirits of them that were preſent; they look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him with Reſpect, and they ſend him home with Praiſes, in the ſame moment that they were <pb n="110" facs="tcp:62282:71"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:62282:71"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:62282:72"/> preparing to make him end his Life in cruel Tortures. A reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute word only makes that change; and ſuch a word well placd, is a great Ornament in a Narration, and has a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Effect. So upon <hi>Fabius</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking <hi>Tarentum, Hannibal,</hi> thô vanquiſh'd, ſpoke this fine Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which look'd as thô he had ſtill been victorious, praiſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to raiſe his Enemy the more:
<note n="*" place="margin">Et <hi>Romani</hi> ſuum habent
<hi>Annibalem,</hi> l. 27. Annal.</note> 
                  <hi>The Romans, ſaid he, have alſo at laſt their Hannibal.</hi> That was a proud way of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting himſelf. Thoſe ſayings are frequent in that <hi>Hiſtorian.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing alſo gives more the Idea of thoſe who ſpeak ſo, when they ſpeak well, nor of him that makes them ſpeak, as when he does it on purpoſe. Here is one of another kind, taken out of <hi>Tacitus,</hi> in that famous Feaſt
<hi>Maſſalina</hi> made to her Lover: In the heat of the rejoicing, and of the Debauchery of that Feaſt, they got an Idiot, whoſe Name was
<hi>Valens,</hi> to climb up to the <pb n="113" facs="tcp:62282:72"/> top of a Tree; and they asked him what he ſaw: <hi>A Tempeſt, ſaid he, which gathers in the Air, and comes from Oſtium.</hi> That word, ſpoken by a Fool, caſt a coldneſs and ſorrow upon the People's Spirits, which diſturb'd all things, thô ſpoken without deſign; for it was a Prognoſtication of the <hi>Emperour</hi>'s return, which happen'd a few days after, and caus'd the
<hi>Empreſs</hi> to be ſtabb'd, tir'd with her infamous Life. Thoſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous ſayings are very accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> being fit to rouze up the Reader's Mind by ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which is ſharp. There are Thouſands of others which an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> employs to embelliſh his Work, and which have eſcap'd my Memory: and I do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſay all that is good in this kind. It is enough to mark thoſe which can give another face to Affairs; to ſearch other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, to give way to other I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea's, and to other Sentiments: In a word, all thoſe fine ſayings, capable of cauſing ſome kind of <pb n="114" facs="tcp:62282:73"/> revolution in the Reader's Mind, to give him Action, and Motion too, being always truly fine, are never out of uſe. The buſineſs is to place them ſo, that they may appear incorporated in a Narration, to play all their part in it; that is to ſay, to make the matter pleaſant, when, of it ſelf, it is barren and diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>XXV. The Sentiments which ought to be allow'd in Hiſtory.</head>
               <p>There are Sentiments which are fit for the Theatre, and are not ſo for <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> becauſe Poetry ſays things as they ſhould be; <hi>Hiſtory</hi> ſays them as they are. So thoſe
<hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> which give their <hi>Heroes</hi> ſuch exquiſite Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are not always the moſt judicious; and whatever is not grounded upon good ſenſe, be it never ſo fine, is not the beſt. So that
<hi>Quintus Curtius</hi> is not always in the right, to repreſent
<hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> ſo admirable. He does not <pb n="115" facs="tcp:62282:73"/> make him act by the meaſure of Prudence, but always puts him upon difficult and perillous Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures<hi>:</hi> Danger charms him; He is not fond of Conqueſts, but of the Glory of Conquering: He might ſurpriſe
<hi>Darius,</hi> by falling upon him in the Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and that way hide his Weakneſs, the Enemies Army being twice in number bigger than his own<hi>:</hi> But that Great Man, who cares leſs to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, than to make People ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire his Bravery, attacks the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> in the middle of the Day; reſolved rather to loſe his Life gloriouſly, than to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by ſurpriſal. <hi>Darius,</hi> after his Overthrow, proffers to divide <hi>Aſia</hi> with him, and offers him his Daughter in Marriage;
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> chuſes rather to purſue his Honour through Perils, than to become Maſter with ſo much Tranquility: He does not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to thoſe Propoſals; he will accept of nothing but what is extraordinary. His
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> does <pb n="116" facs="tcp:62282:74"/> him a great deal of Honour: ſure, a little likelihood would have done well mixt with ſo much Glory: Does not he make his <hi>Heroe</hi> more Fool-hardy than wiſe, and more adventurous than ambitious? Without doubt he ſound that way finer; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, he has given us reaſon to doubt, whether it is a <hi>Romance,</hi> or an <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> which he has left us; for he puſhes things too far. So important it is for an Author in all things to make Reaſon his Standard, and to follow rather the Nature of things, than the fine Imaginations of his own Wit. Let not <hi>Hiſtory</hi> then au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize the ridiculous Conceits of falſe Glory, which cauſes vain People to commit ſo many Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, the moſt part of which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes little to true Honour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have no ſenſe of it. Let it not attribute to a <hi>Mounte-bank</hi> the Sentiments of a ſolid man, nor the Vertues of a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick Heroe</hi> to a true Knight. Great men are ſubject to form <pb n="117" facs="tcp:62282:74"/> to themſelves Idea's of Glory, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their own fancy, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the failing of their Vanity. But the Publick Intereſt ought to be dearer to him who governs, than his own Glory: And the true Honour of a great Prince, is to gain the People's Hearts rather than their Fears. Thoſe are the Sentiments which ought to reign moſt in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> that it may become a Leſſon of Clemency to Princes, and a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of Reaſon and good Senſe to all People. Let not an <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> therefore be miſtaken; let him firſt diſtinguiſh true Honour from falſe, and in the Maxims of this Life praiſe only what is good; Let him clear the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Errors, without becoming himſelf a Slave to Popular Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents: Let him never ſuffer himſelf to judge of things by their Events, without running up to their Spring; but let him open their very Principles: Let him be careful of doing Juſtice to the true and pretended Merit, that <pb n="118" facs="tcp:62282:75"/> he may not impoſe on Poſterity, which gives Credit to what is ſaid, without any examination, and ſticks to the Litteral Senſe<hi>:</hi> Let him never ſhew great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, without giving notice of Cauſes, and without diſcovering their true Motives. Sometimes it is nothing, or at leaſt, but little; but People lack to ſee great things come from ſmall Principles, as
<hi>Dionyſius Halicarnaſſaeus</hi> teaches in the Fifth Book of his
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> on the occaſion of the Revolution of Government from the Kings of <hi>Rome,</hi> which happen'd through the Inſolence of Young
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>T. Liv.</hi> l. 1. Ann.</note>
                  <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin,</hi> and the Pride of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. That is the Spirit which ought to reign in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and the Maxim which muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd therein. Let us ſee its Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:62282:75"/>
               <head>XXVI. How the Genius of an Historian muſt be.</head>
               <p>Nothing can be writ conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> without a Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us; that makes all in that Art, as well as in others; and it is only that way that <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh themſelves from one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. A ſmall Genius will make but little of a great Subject; and he that has a great Genius, will make a ſmall Subject appear great.
<note n="*" place="margin">Arduum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deturres geſtas ſcribere, quod facta dictis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aequanda ſunt, <hi>Saluſt.</hi> proem. Bell.
<hi>Catil.</hi>
                  </note> To write <hi>Hiſtory</hi> well therefore, a man muſt have an univerſal Genius, capable of great Idea's, to form to himſelf a great Model, and great Deſigns. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory</hi> is a thing of importance
<note n="†" place="margin">Magnum quid Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am recte ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, &amp; ſummis Oratoris pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prium, <hi>Cic.</hi> l. 2. de Orat.</note>, ſays <hi>Cicero,</hi> and the buſineſs of a Man above the Common Level. And when <hi>Lucian,</hi> who was one of the fineſt Wits of his Age, which produc'd ſo many great men, confeſſes, that his Genius was too weak for <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and to attain to that Perfection which it requires. He frights me, by cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating <pb n="120" facs="tcp:62282:76"/> in me a juſt apprehenſion of the difficulty which attends it: For if that Author, which has written nothing but what is admirable, and gives Rules ſo full of good ſenſe for the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> acknowledges that he is not capable of ſuſtaining the weight of ſo great a work, what will become of thoſe that in one day ſet up for <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> without any knowledge of what is Eſſential in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> as he ſays it happen'd in that War in <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia,</hi> which produc'd ſo many Authors, through an Itch of writing, which at that time was a common Diſeaſe? But the Times are chang'd, ſays he; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more difficult than for a man to compile a Work which all future Ages may eſteem, as <hi>Thucydides</hi> has done. For what ſtrength of Spirit is requiſite to ſpeak the Truth, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Paraphraſes, as thoſe do, who have not Souls great enough to be clear and candid, and to ſpeak things as they are? What
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:62282:76"/> firmneſs to unmask Vice, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally diſguis'd with Diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? What Sagacity to diſcover the bottom of the Genius of them we ſpeak of, without ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the exterior part of the Perſon, which ſeldom ſignifies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing? But when the buſineſs is to diſtinguiſh People and Times by what is eſſential in their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, how neceſſary is a clear and diſtinguiſhing head? As for Example, in relating the Civil Wars of <hi>Rome,</hi> not to confound the Spirit of the
<hi>Commonwealth</hi> with that of <hi>Monarchy;</hi> the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſs of the one with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency of the other; not to write the Reign of
<hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth, which is no way ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to Superſtition, like that of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Eleventh, whoſe Character was Superſtition it ſelf; not to repreſent <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> like <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, but to mark the Times and the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by the difference there is between them. What integrity, exactly to do Juſtice to Vice and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:62282:77"/> Virtue, to diſtinguiſh the true from the pretended Merit, and to uſe ones ſelf to weigh the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, without any regard to the Perſons? What Judgment, to take always the right ſide, to turn things to the right ſenſe, to chuſe always what is moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid; to interpoſe your Judgement upon the matter in agitation, without forcing the Reader, by any prejudices, to touch tender Points with that niceneſs of Wit which can only be the Effect of an exquiſite ſenſe; not to load your Diſcourſe with too much Matter, which might chance to ſpoil the Spirit of it, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving way to any Reflection what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, made either by you, or any other Reader; to know how to find the true knot in every buſineſs, without miſtaking your ſelf in its explanation; not to deliver great Actions upon frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Motives; not to hide falſe Thoughts under a florid Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; to avoid any thing which ſeems ſtudied and forc'd, and to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:62282:77"/> follow in all things that beam of light and underſtanding which gives an Idea of the diſcerning Faculty of the
<hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a good Opinion of his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities. So that the moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary part in <hi>Hiſtory</hi> is Judgment. An
<hi>Orator</hi> may forget himſelf in the flights of his Eloquence, and venture bold ſtroaks, which may paſs upon a multitude of People, who are pleas'd with nothing more than boldneſs. A <hi>Poet</hi> may ramble from his
<hi>Text,</hi> and has no great neceſſity to be always wiſe. The
<hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> who ſpeaks only in cold Blood, ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to be Maſter of himſelf, and to ſay nothing but what is juſt nothing, in fine, requires ſo much Senſe, ſo much Reaſon, ſo much Wit and Judgment, and ſo many other Qualities, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to perfection, as
<hi>Hiſtory;</hi> and after all is done, an happy Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, endued with all thoſe Perfections, is not ſufficient, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a great knowledge of the World. It was only the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation <pb n="124" facs="tcp:62282:78"/>
                  <hi>Polybius</hi> had with <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio</hi> and <hi>Lelius,</hi> that made him ſo able an <hi>Hiſtorian.</hi> We have in <hi>Thucydides</hi> and
<hi>Livy</hi> accompliſh'd Patterns of that Genius requir'd in
<hi>Hiſtory.</hi> Antiquity has nothing more finiſh'd in that kind. There is hardly any thing wanting in the one, or in the other, but that
<hi>Thucydides</hi> is yet more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere than <hi>Livy,</hi> and the laſt more natural than the firſt. <hi>Tacitus</hi> is admirable in his way;
<hi>Lipſius</hi> prefers him before all others: Every body is not of his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. One may ſay in general, That he is an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> of a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Rank, who has a great deal of agreeableneſs amongſt great failings; but his defects are ſomewhat hidden under a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Genius which ſhines in all he ſays, and under a loftineſs not well to be deſcrib'd, which raiſe him above many Authors more exact, and more natural than himſelf. He has his Party and his Admirers. It is true, that he pleaſes men of Fancy and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, <pb n="125" facs="tcp:62282:78"/> but not thoſe that have moſt Judgment, nor thoſe that love good Senſe rather than Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes. Among Moderns, I find <hi>Mariana, Davila, Fra Paolo,</hi> have an admirable Genius for <hi>Hiſtory. Mariana</hi> has the gift of thinking, and of ſaying nobly what he thinks and ſpeaks, and of giving a Character of greatneſs to what runs in his Mind. <hi>Davila</hi> brings good Circumſtances of things, diſcourſes juſtly enough upon the Subjects he treats of, and carries on his Diſcourſe in a continued Strain, which gives him that obliging Air which he has a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove others. <hi>Fra Paolo,</hi> in his
<hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> gives what Colours he pleaſes to what he ſays: No body ever had that Art in a more eminent degree. He ſhews alſo a great Capacity, in ſearching to the bottom the Matters of Learning which he has in hand, to give his Readers a perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof: No body ever writ with more Skill, nor with
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:62282:79"/> more Wit, and never with leſs Juſtice and Truth. He is a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate man, who employ'd all his Art in hiding his Paſſion: He made a jeſt in every thing, that he might not be thought to be angry; but he falls into another Defect<hi>:</hi> He raileth too much, in a Subject ſo ſerious as his is; for his Paſſion is ſeen in every thing he ſpeaks. So that <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> with his great Genius, has the moſt Vicious Character that can be in the way of writing <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> where nothing is leſs pardonable than Enmity. An <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> is no longer believ'd, when once he is thought too paſſionate; which gives occaſion of examining the Honeſty which is neceſſary for him that pretends to write.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:62282:79"/>
               <head>XXVII. The Hiſtorians Morality.</head>
               <p>As every one ought to lay down to himſelf a Rule of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, according to his Genius, the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi>'s Mind is known by his Principles. You muſt firſt of all take it for granted, that there are but few who have hearts noble enough, neither to fear nor hope for any thing; and who will value Truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Intereſt, which is the moſt general Spring of all the wrong Judgments men make in things they ſpeak of. This is what you ought to think upon firſt, when you take upon you to inſtruct the Publick; and it is the chiefeſt Maxim an <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ought to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to himſelf. That being well eſtabliſh'd, he ought to think on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to get Credit in People's good Opinion, and to give a Colour of Truth to all he ſays. It is that chiefly to which all his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours ought to tend; which
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:62282:80"/> he will never effect, but by eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing his Reputation: And it is not by Proteſtations of being ſincere, that he ſhall demonſtrate his Integrity<hi>:</hi> It is by making appear in all his words, the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs of his heart, and the honeſty of his mind. Therefore nothing ought to come from him but what has the ſtamp of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Reaſon. The Love he ought to have for Truth, ought to be the Rules of all his Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and of all his Idea's.
<note n="*" place="margin">Ne qua ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picio gratiae ſit, ne qua ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multatis, <hi>Cic.</hi> de Orat.</note> Let him always ſpeak like an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man; let him never ſpeak any thing that can injure Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity or Integrity; let him keep cloſe to the Sentiments which the ſevereſt Honour can inſpire; and let nothing ever appear in his words that may raiſe a queſtion of his Probity and Truth; let him ſpeak ſo that People may believe him to ſpeak true as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as he ſpeaks, through an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, that he is not capable of impoſing. No man can ever err with ſo good Principles. It <pb n="129" facs="tcp:62282:80"/> is by ſo pure a Method that
<hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydides</hi> did ſet up the Reputation of his ſincerity through all fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Ages, and that he has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd the Credit of all People. It is his Zeal for Religion, and Reſpect for the Gods, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in all
<hi>Xenophon</hi>'s Books, that engages People not to queſtion what he ſays, being perſuaded, that a man, who has the Love of Piety ſo deeply engraven in his heart, cannot lye. <hi>Polybius</hi> takes more liberty: He relates, as Fables, the Sentiments People had of the Gods, and of Hell; thinking, that way, to deſtroy them. And it is rather by his Honeſty that
<hi>Livy</hi> perſuades, than by his great Capacity: through all the Intrigues, Intereſts, Paſſions, and other Extravagancies of thoſe men he ſpeaks of, there appears a Probity, which ſhews him as well honeſt as a good <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> One may perceive in the moſt hidden parts of the Hearts of thoſe he deſcribes, the bottom of his own; and amongſt the falſe <pb n="130" facs="tcp:62282:81"/> lights he diſcovers in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, he never has any falſe aims; he judges of all things rightly, his Judgment being as true as his Intentions are juſt. <hi>Tacitus</hi> is not of that Character; he is a great ſhuffler, who hides a very bad Mind under a very great Wit<hi>:</hi> he miſtakes always true Merit, becauſe he hardly knows any other than that of Ability; and it is Policy more than Truth, makes him ſpeak, beſides his want of Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Neighbour: When he ſpeaks of the Gods, he ſhews nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Piety nor Religion, as is ſeen in his Diſcourſe upon Fate againſt Providence, <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Annal.</hi> and imputes all things to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and the Stars, concerning
<hi>Traſullus,</hi> Aſtrologer to <hi>Tyberius,</hi> who was become his Secretary at <hi>Capraea.</hi> So difficult it is for an ill man to be a good
<hi>Hiſtorian;</hi> for they are almoſt the ſame Principles of the one and of the other. So when an Author takes his Pen, he takes upon himſelf
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:62282:81"/> the Character of a Publick Man; and he ſtrips himſelf of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, whenſoever he takes up the Sentiments of a Private Perſon, to regard himſelf, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge his own quarrels; as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copius,</hi> who being diſſatisfied with the <hi>Emperour Juſtinian,</hi> and the Empreſs <hi>Theodora,</hi> gives way to his own Paſſion, and corrupts Truth: Or, to follow private prejudices, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> and
<hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorite,</hi> which made uſe of their <hi>Hiſtories</hi> to eſtabliſh their own Errors<hi>:</hi> Or, to flatter thoſe whom you mean to pleaſe, as <hi>Buchanan,</hi> who in his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> blemiſhes the Honour of <hi>Mary,</hi> to gratifie Queen
<hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and as <hi>Fra Paolo,</hi> who makes his
<hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory</hi> of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr againſt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Religion; where he ſhews a Chain of Invectives upon Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives, to revenge himſelf upon the Pope, becauſe he had not made him a Cardinal, after the hopes he had given him of it. <hi>Paulus Jovius</hi> was a man that <pb n="132" facs="tcp:62282:82"/> purſued his Intereſts, Penſioner to <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, unjuſt, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, a great Flatterer<hi>:</hi> The Pictures he made of the moſt conſiderable Perſons in his <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> are Pieces which he pick'd up to compoſe the Lives of Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Men, on purpoſe to get Money; they are done according as he was pay'd for them. <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardin</hi> is angry with
<hi>France; San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doval</hi> makes <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth a moſt Catholick Prince, whilſt that Monarch foments <hi>Hereſie</hi> in <hi>Germany:</hi> all this becauſe <hi>Paulus</hi> the Third had vex'd him. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brera</hi> praiſes <hi>Philip</hi> the Second for his Piety, who favour'd
<hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> againſt <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which he hindred from being Queen, becauſe ſhe favour'd the <hi>French;</hi> and ſo overthrew the Catholick Religion in <hi>England. Herrera</hi> is a
<hi>Fanſaroon,</hi> and is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to his Nation. In fine, there are hardly any <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> but have their own Inclinations and A verſions: It goes hard with them to alter their Sentiments, <pb n="133" facs="tcp:62282:82"/> and they make <hi>Elogiums</hi> by Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, or Satyrs, as their own Minds are diſpoſed.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marcellin.</hi> in ejus Vita.</note> There are but few like <hi>Thucydides,</hi> who by a Principle of Right and Equity, praiſes <hi>Pericles,</hi> as he deſerves, thô he had us'd him very ill; and does always Juſtice to the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians,</hi> who baniſhed him to <hi>Thracia,</hi> where he died. It is a man without Paſſions, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to himſelf only the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Poſterity, for the Mark he aims at, and his Work, and who has no other deſire than that of Truth; wherein he is an honeſter man than all others; for he never renounces his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity. <hi>Livy</hi> favours <hi>Pompey</hi> more than <hi>Caeſar, Dio</hi> favours <hi>Caeſar</hi> more than <hi>Pompey. Ammianus Marcellinus</hi> is an everlaſting Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper of <hi>Julian</hi> the
<hi>Apoſtate,</hi> but cries out always againſt <hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> his Succeſſor, becauſe he was a Chriſtian. <hi>Euſebius</hi> never ſhews <hi>Conſtantine</hi> but on the right ſide; <hi>Zozimus</hi> ſhews him always the other way. <hi>Procopius</hi> made <pb n="134" facs="tcp:62282:83"/> his Idol of <hi>Bellizary, Egynhart</hi> of <hi>Charles the Great, Sandoval</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, <hi>Strada of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Farneze:</hi> In a word, each <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> makes himſelf an
<hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roe</hi> after his own palate, whom he looks upon as his Creature; and that he might make him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the better, he ſtudies to make him more admirable. It is this which renders moſt <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aies</hi> ſuſpicious, all <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſionate; and there being hardly any ſincere ones, becauſe there are few diſintereſted. Thoſe that are above Intereſt, let them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be blinded with the deſire of pleaſing; and the care they have of their Reputation, leads them into other Extreams.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſephus</hi> non tam ſtudebat vera ſcribere, quam credibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia: hac cauſa fuit cur praete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rierit miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, quod apud Infideles fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem non erant habitum, &amp; narravit fabulas, quas putavit iis magis probabiles futuras. <hi>Leo Caſſ.</hi> diſp. de tranſl. ſacr. leg. <hi>c.</hi> 36.</note> 
                  <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> in the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſuppreſſes true Miracles, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who would not have believ'd them; and ſuppoſes things leſs true, becauſe he thought them fitter for the palates, and according to their <pb n="135" facs="tcp:62282:83"/> apprehenſion. An
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins himſelf, if he thinks to be eſtabliſh'd that way: you muſt ſay things as they are; woe to the unbelievers: For nothing is worſe in a man who profeſſes to give an account of Truth to the Publick, than to profane it thus. In fine, let nothing ſlaviſh ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, nor of Cowardice, in the Sentiments or Inclinations of the <hi>Hiſtorian;</hi> for nothing gives a worſe Opinion of his Probity. But thô I do not approve the Flatterers of Great men, as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius,</hi> who ſhews nothing in <hi>Conſtantine</hi> but what deſerves prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, who nevertheleſs had great failings; my Opinion is, that they ought to be forgiven in ſome things: For thô one ought to ſpeak nothing but what is true, yet he ought not to ſay all the Truth. <hi>Quintus Curtius</hi> might have let alone the Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies he related of <hi>Alexander.</hi> There are ſome priviledg'd Heads which a body ought to reſpect; let us ſpeak of them handſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <pb n="136" facs="tcp:62282:84"/> and not irreverently: We may expoſe their Faults, but it muſt be in a way that does not ſcandalize their Dignity, nor hurt the Reſpect due to their Grandeur. <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſays ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dirty things of <hi>Tyberius,</hi> that <hi>Boccalinus</hi> cannot ſuffer him. That which <hi>Lampridius</hi> tells of the Emperours
<hi>Heliogabalus</hi> and <hi>Caracalla,</hi> makes his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible; and <hi>Platina</hi> ſhews but little judgment in his manner of treating the <hi>Popes.</hi> All the World will not be of my ſide, but wiſe men will; and I am perſuaded, that what Merit ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever there is in being ſincere, a man would render himſelf ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous to be ſo in all things. But, as an Author never praiſes well, unleſs he does it nicely, ſo he that beſtows his Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon meaner Actions, and not upon thoſe which are eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, and which appear praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, ſhall always find the Publick out of humour, becauſe it will never endure thoſe prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <pb n="137" facs="tcp:62282:84"/> which it does not find juſtly beſtow'd: Therefore good Senſe adviſes never to praiſe, but by a ſincere account of praiſable A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> de Conſer. Hiſt.</note> All the World knows the Adventure of <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> one of the Captains of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> who read to him the <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory</hi> of the Battel which that Prince fought againſt <hi>Porus. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> who was then in his Barge upon <hi>Hydaſpus,</hi> enrag'd with the Flatteries of that <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian,</hi> ſnatch'd the Book out of his hands, and threw it into the River; adding, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to be ſerv'd ſo too, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo impudent as to praiſe him ſo ill, by attributing to him falſe Conqueſts, as if there had been want of true ones. This is very near the Morality I could wiſh in an <hi>Hiſtorian;</hi> or, at leaſt, it would be my Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, in caſe I had the Fancy to write <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and that I were of a Genius good enough for it. I would, in fine, be ſo modeſt, that there might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear <pb n="138" facs="tcp:62282:85"/> Honeſty, and never Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in my Sentiments; which makes me to have no patience with the Extravagancy of that
<hi>Hiſtorian Photius</hi> ſpeaks of, who preparing himſelf to write the
<hi>Hiſtory of Alexander,</hi> promiſes, that his Style ſhall not be worſe than the Actions of his <hi>Heroe.</hi> After all is done, it makes a man loſe almoſt the Fancy of writing, if he has any Senſe, when he ſees the judgment <hi>Dionyſius Halicarnaſſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> made of
<hi>Thucydides</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> for there is no judicious Author, but that Critick will make him tremble. Theſe are the Notions I got to my ſelf in reading <hi>Hiſtories.</hi> I am not ſo vain as to pretend to give them for Maxims: They are only thoughts, and perhaps but ill digeſted, which may become good by the good uſe that may be made of them. Here follow the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments one may have upon the moſt conſiderable
<hi>Hiſtorians.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:62282:85"/>
               <head>XXVIII. Judgment of Hiſtorians.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Herodotus</hi> is the firſt who has given a reaſonable form to <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> and his merit is, to have led the way to others. His Style is pure and eloquent.
<note n="*" place="margin">Dulcis, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didus, fuſus
<hi>Herodotus. Fab.</hi> l. 10. c. 1. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</hi> 1. 3.</note>
                  <hi>Athenaeus</hi> praiſes him for the Charms of his Diſcourſe. His Subject is great and vaſt; for it compaſſes Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Kingdoms, Empires; the Affairs of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia.</hi> He is not very exact in what he ſays, becauſe he contains too much matter; but I find in him a ſincerity which is not very common, becauſe he uſes <hi>Greeks</hi> and
<hi>Barbarians,</hi> his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen and Strangers, without any ſhew of Partiality.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Platarch.</hi> de malign.
<hi>Herod.</hi>
                  </note> I find <hi>Plutarch</hi> deals with him too ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly, when he makes him to have an ill meaning in moſt part of his Conjectures; but it is only Envy and Revenge makes him uſe him ſo, becauſe he u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ill his Countrey of <hi>Boeotia,</hi> in
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:62282:86"/> his <hi>Hiſtory.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Laudatur ab omnibus ut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſincerus &amp; gravis; hujus nemo neque verborum, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſententia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum gravita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem imitatur. <hi>Cic.</hi> de opt. Orar.</note>
                  <hi>Thucydides</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act in his way of writing, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in things he relates, ſincere, and not ſway'd by Intereſt: he has Greatneſs, Nobleneſs, Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty in his Style; he is always ſtrict, but his ſtrictneſs has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is great in it: The Truth is, that his Subject is leſſer, and more limited than that of <hi>Herodotus.</hi> It is only through a Spirit of Partiality, that <hi>Dionyſius Halicarnaſſaeus</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers <hi>Herodotus</hi> before
<hi>Thucydides,</hi> the firſt being his Countreyman<hi>:</hi> For my own part, I find him the moſt accompliſh'd <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the
<hi>Greeks. Xenophon</hi> is pure in his Language, Natural, agreeable in his Compoſition; his Mind is eaſie, rich, full of a deep knowledge, a clear imagination, a juſt turn; but he is neither great nor elevated. Good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are not always well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in his <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> where he makes ignorant and brutiſh Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſpeak like Philoſophers. <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> tells us, that <hi>Scipio</hi> could not <pb n="141" facs="tcp:62282:86"/> part with him, when once he had him in his hands: <hi>Longinus</hi> gives it as his Character, That he conceiv'd things happily. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all is done, he is a well-ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed <hi>Hiſtorian;</hi> and it was by the reading of his
<hi>Hiſtory,</hi> that <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Lucullus</hi> became ſo great Captains. <hi>Polybius</hi> diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes well; he is provided with good and fine Materials, but he does not manage them ſo well as the others I ſpoke of but now: He ought, for all that, to be prais'd for the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea
<hi>Brutus</hi> had of him, who at the height of his Misfortunes, did paſs whole Nights in the reading and ſtudying of them. His De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is not ſo much to write an <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> as an Inſtruction how to govern a Countrey, as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſays at the end of his Firſt Book; and he leaves there, in a manner, the Character of an <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian,</hi> which obliges him to make a kind of an Apology in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Ninth Book, about his way of writing <hi>Hiſtory:</hi> his Style is much neglected.
<hi>Dionyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> 
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:62282:87"/> 
                  <hi>Halycarnaſſaeus</hi> ſhews, in his Book of <hi>Roman</hi> Antiquities, a deep Senſe, Learning and Conduct, which is not common; he is exact, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and judicious, truer than <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> and of great weight: But, to conclude, he is very tedious in his Speeches. <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> is a man of great Character; but he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains too many things, pretending to make an Abridgement of
<hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> of <hi>Timaeus,</hi> of <hi>Calliſthenes,</hi> of
<hi>Theopompus,</hi> and others. <hi>Philo</hi> and <hi>Joſephus</hi> are Authors of an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Eloquence: They were both <hi>Jews,</hi> who had too great a deſire to pleaſe <hi>Pagans,</hi> by accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modating themſelves like Slaves to their Humour and Taſte. <hi>Arrian</hi> does but Copy <hi>Xenophon,</hi> and is an affected Imitator of his ways: he has made Seven Books of the Conqueſts of <hi>Alexander,</hi> as <hi>Xenophon</hi> did of <hi>Cyrus</hi>'s: <hi>Appianus</hi> dabbl'd in all the <hi>Greek Hiſtorians,</hi> and with that hodge-podge has made to himſelf a Style which reſembles no bodies. <hi>Scaliger</hi> calls him the Thief of
<hi>Hiſtories;</hi> he <pb n="143" facs="tcp:62282:87"/> took the beſt of his Book out of <hi>Plutarch</hi>'s: but, after all, there is in him a vaſt deal of matter. <hi>Dio Caſſius</hi> crack'd his Credit with almoſt every body, becauſe of the extraordinary things which he writes without any diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for inſtead of cleaving ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Truth, he runs from the very appearance of it, in that place of the 66<hi>th</hi> Book of his
<hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi> where he ſays, That <hi>Veſpaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> cur'd a blind man by ſpitting upon his Eyes. <hi>Procopius</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act in what he ſays, becauſe he accompanied <hi>Belliſarius</hi> in the Wars, and was an Eye-witneſs of his great Actions: but he is too dry in his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> which looks more like a Journal than <hi>Hiſtory.</hi> He ſatisfied his own Fancy by writing that private <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story;</hi> but his Modeſty was great in his ſuppreſſing it: for the thing which he took pains to hide du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Life, was made publick after his Death; wherein he is not altogether inexcuſable. Moſt part of thoſe who have written the
<hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stary</hi> 
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:62282:88"/> of <hi>Byzantium,</hi> either took Copies one by another, as <hi>Agathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, Cedrenus, John Curopalatus;</hi> or are not very exact; and they come nothing near the Dignity, the Nobleneſs, the Diſtinguiſhing, and the Faithfulneſs of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Greeks.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Subtiliſſimus brevitatis arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fex
<hi>Saluſtius,</hi> proprietatum in verbis reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentiſſimus.
<hi>Gell.</hi>
                  </note> Amongſt the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins, Salust</hi> looks great, exact, of an admirable Judgment. No bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ever expreſs'd the ſenſible, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act, ſevere Style of <hi>Thucydides,</hi> better than he.
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Saluſtius</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo nequam, ſed graviſſimus alienae
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>uxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae objurgator.
<hi>Lact.</hi> l. 2. de falſ. Rel.</note> He is ſtiff ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in his Expreſſions, but not inſipid: his being ſo ſhort, makes him leſs clear: His Method is good, and he gives weight to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing he ſays: His Thoughts are always fine, thô his Manners be bad; declaring always in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of Virtue, and Dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of Vice. I find him a little too peeviſh with his Countrey, and ill affected to his Neighbour; but, for all that, he is a very great man. <hi>Caeſar</hi> had the fineſt way of expreſſing himſelf that ever was. Pedants are in the right in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him, for the inimitable pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <pb n="145" facs="tcp:62282:88"/> of his Style; but I ſtill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire him the more, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs of his Senſe, no body ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ever written better. He is almoſt the only Author that is free from Impertinencies. He ſpeaks of himſelf but as an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent body, and nothing diſagrees in the wiſe Character he has ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. It is true, that he is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together an <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> but it is true too, that he is a fine Model to write <hi>Hiſtory</hi> by. It is a great Honour for that incomparable Author, that <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> and
<hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth have buſied themſelves in the tranſlating of his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Gaules. Livy</hi> is the moſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd of all, becauſe he has all the great Parts of an
<hi>Hiſtorian;</hi> the Imagination fine, the Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion noble, an exact Senſe, with an admirable Eloquence. None but great Idea's come in his Mind; he fills the Imagination of his Readers with what he ſays: that way he gains People's Hearts, and moves their Souls; <pb n="146" facs="tcp:62282:89"/> and he has the greateſt Genius for <hi>History,</hi> and is one of the greateſt Maſters of Eloquence that ever was.
<note n="*" place="margin">In <hi>Tito Livio</hi> putat ineſſe
<hi>Pollio</hi> quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Patavini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem. Fab.</hi> l. 8. c. 1.</note> I do not apprehend <hi>Aſinius Pollia</hi>'s meaning, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes him a Countrey Air, which ſmells of <hi>Lombardy.</hi> His great ſtrength is, to make Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple taſte what he ſays, by draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Readers to his own Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, by infuſing into their Minds his Fears and his Hopes, giving them all his Paſſion by the Art he has of moving the moſt hidden Springs of Hearts. <hi>Tacitus</hi> deſcribes things in a way quite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from others; but he ſticks too cloſe to great things, to avoid falling into ſmall ones, which ought not to be neglected. His thoughts are good, but he is not always happy enough to expreſs himſelf neatly. He is too much a Philoſopher. He ſpeaks high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of every thing: If means Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was in his hands, he could not ſpeak otherwiſe<hi>:</hi> and he morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes always upon other People's foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs<hi>:</hi> and that he may ſpare no
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:62282:89"/> body, he detracts from all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. How many Spirits has he ſpoil'd by the deſire of ſtudying Politicks, which he inſpir'd ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny People with, and which is the vaineſt of all Studies: 'Tis that ruin'd ſo many <hi>Spaniards,</hi> as <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio Perez,</hi> and ſo many
<hi>Italians,</hi> as <hi>Machiavel, Ammirato,</hi> and others. It is only by the fineneſs of his Style, that this laſt pleaſes ſo much thoſe of ſtrong minds, and ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thoſe that are not ſo; for he gives diſtaſts by the ſubtilty of his Diſcourſes and Reflections. He is ſo obſcure in his Expreſſions, that a man muſt be extreamly vers'd in his Style, to know how to unwrap his Thoughts.
<note n="*" place="margin">Evenit non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunquam &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquid granda inveniat, qui ſemper quaerit quod nimium eſt. <hi>Fab.</hi> l. 2. c.
13.</note> His manner of Criticiſing is fine of it ſelf; but his conſtant cenſuring of all things makes it become courſe. He is elevated, becauſe his thoughts are always high mounted: It is only that way that he impoſes; and it is not ſo much to pleaſe, and to inſtruct, that he writes, as to make himſelf be admir'd: he has ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extraordinary, which cauſes
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:62282:90"/> People to excuſe moſt part of his failings. But there are ſo many things to be ſaid of that Author, good and bad, that there is no end in ſpeaking of him. It is a kind of Wit, which is of uſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a ſhew; that does not fit the ordinary Commerce of men. <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Curtius</hi> deſerves praiſes for his being ſincere: he ſays what is good and bad in <hi>Alexander,</hi> and never ſuffers the Merits of his
<hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes</hi> to prevent him. If there be any thing to be found fault with in his <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> it is, that it is too nicely finiſh't. But for all that, he did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in the Deſcriptions of Manners, which he has done with an Air a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable and natural. That Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Perfections which is found in thoſe great Men, was loſt in the following Ages. <hi>Juſtin,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Compiler, thinking to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect himſelf to an <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> does only touch things as he paſſes by. He knows a great deal; he ſays things ſenſibly; and he collected many Actions, which otherwiſe might have been loſt. Moſt part <pb n="149" facs="tcp:62282:90"/> of the Authors;
<hi>Hiſtoriae Auguſtae,</hi> fix'd their Minds to write Lives; as
<hi>Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Herodian</hi> amongſt the <hi>Greeks, Suetonius</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Nepos</hi> among the <hi>Latins;</hi> and ſo loſt the Character of <hi>Hiſtorians.</hi> There came nothing after that, but ſingle <hi>Chroniclers, Copiers, Compilers,</hi> and ſuch whoſe Names were known by a courſe knowledge they gave of their Ages, to whom the Planet of <hi>Hiſtory</hi> was not very favourable, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing fine nor reaſonable in them. There was but little Truth found in the Modern
<hi>Greeks,</hi> who became Viſionaries, and related ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Adventures, to pleaſe their own Fancies. The Love of Study, which flouriſh'd again in the late Ages, reviv'd again a number of good and ſenſible <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> who by ſtudying Ancient Authors, and ruling themſelves by them, gain'd more Reputation than their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors Among thoſe that excell'd then, that which is peculiar to
<hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines,</hi> is, that he wrote with good ſenſe and ſincerity.
<hi>Paulus Aemili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſpeaks purely, but is ſuperficial<hi>:</hi>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:62282:91"/> 
                  <hi>Paulus Jovius</hi> follows only his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and his Intereſt: <hi>Machiavel</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act enough in his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>Florence;</hi> his Wit carries it above his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the reſt. He does not do Juſtice entirely to <hi>Caſtruccio Caſtrucci,</hi> whom he treats as an Enemy of his Countrey. <hi>Mariana,</hi> in his <hi>History</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> was out-done by no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern, neither for the Greatneſs of the Deſign, nor for the Nobleneſs of the Style. <hi>Buchanan</hi> is a little too much like a Slave in his imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Livy.</hi> He ſtole from the Ancients what he has that is good. He writes very ſenſibly, yet has not his thoughts elevated. His long Quotations in the Third Book, do not pleaſe every body, no more than the large account he gives in the Second Book of the Notion of the Countrey he ſpeaks of. The <hi>Germans</hi> have vaſt Projects about their <hi>Hiſtories,</hi> and nothing reduc'd into the Natural Order, which an exact Deſign requires. One may find in moſt part of the
<hi>Spaniards</hi> a Spirit of Partiality for their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which renders them much ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. <pb n="151" facs="tcp:62282:91"/> The <hi>Italians</hi> are rich in particular <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of the ſeveral States which compoſe
<hi>Italy;</hi> but they have no compleat Body of <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story.</hi> There begins to appear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us ſome beams of hopes to have ſome accompliſhed <hi>Historian,</hi> by the approbation the Publick gives to thoſe that write now.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
